<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>As you were, or, The Lord General Cromwel and the grand officers of the armie their remembrancer wherein as in a glass they may see the faces of their soules spotted with apostacy, ambitious breach of promise, and hocus-pocus-juggleing with the honest soldiers and the rest of the free-people of England : to the end that haveing seene their deformed and fearfull visage, they may be returning to doe their first pretended workes, wipe of their spots, mend their deformities &amp; regaine their lost credit : in a word, save themselves and the gaspeing libertyes of the surprized and enslaved English nation : least enlargement and deliverance arise to the English from another place, but they and their fathers house shall be destroyed : Ester 4. and 14. : all which is contained in a letter directed to the Lord Generall Cromwel, to be communicated to the grandees of his army / written by L. Colonel John Libvrne May 1652 ...</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2084</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1524</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13436666</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13436666</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99537</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48453)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99537)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 464:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>As you were, or, The Lord General Cromwel and the grand officers of the armie their remembrancer wherein as in a glass they may see the faces of their soules spotted with apostacy, ambitious breach of promise, and hocus-pocus-juggleing with the honest soldiers and the rest of the free-people of England : to the end that haveing seene their deformed and fearfull visage, they may be returning to doe their first pretended workes, wipe of their spots, mend their deformities &amp; regaine their lost credit : in a word, save themselves and the gaspeing libertyes of the surprized and enslaved English nation : least enlargement and deliverance arise to the English from another place, but they and their fathers house shall be destroyed : Ester 4. and 14. : all which is contained in a letter directed to the Lord Generall Cromwel, to be communicated to the grandees of his army / written by L. Colonel John Libvrne May 1652 ...</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>May 1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99537:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99537:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AS YOU WERE OR The Lord General CROMWEL and the <hi>Grand Officers</hi> of the <hi>Armie</hi> their REMEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BRANCER. Wherein, as in a glaſs they may ſee the <hi>faces of their Soules</hi> ſpotted with <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, Ambitious breach of promiſe,</hi> and hocus-pocus-<hi>juggleing</hi> with the honeſt <hi>Soldiers,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Free-people of England.</hi> to the end that, haveing ſeene their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and <hi>fearfull viſage,</hi> they may by returning to doe their firſt <hi>pretended</hi> workes, wipe of their <hi>ſpots,</hi> mend their <hi>deformities</hi> &amp; regaine their <hi>loſt Credit;</hi> in a word, ſave themſelves and the <hi>gaſpeing Libertyes</hi> of the ſurprized and <hi>enslaved English Nation:</hi> leaſt enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement and deliverance ariſe to the English from another place, but they and their Fathers houſe shall be deſtroyed. Eſter 4. and 14.</p>
            <p>All which is conteined in a Letter directed to the Lord Generall Cromwel, to be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the Grandees of his Army, written by L. Colonel JOHN LILBVRNE May 1652 from his Lodging in the pleaſaunt Citty of REFUGE ſeated upon the bankes of the renowned River <hi>Rhine,</hi> &amp; commonly called by name VIANEN.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Exodus <hi>9:34, 35.</hi>
               </bibl> And when Pharaoh ſaw that the rain, and the haile, and the thunders were ceaſed, he sinned yit more, and hardned his heart, he and his ſervants. Neither would he let the children of Iſrael go, as the Lord had ſpoken by Moſes.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ezekiel <hi>16:48:51:52.</hi>
               </bibl> As I live, ſaith the Lord God, <hi>(to Jeruſalem)</hi> Sodom thy Siſter hath not done, the nor hir Daughters, as thou haſt done, thou and thy Daughters. Neither hath Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria committed half of thy sin, but thou haſt multiplyed thine abominations more then they, and haſt Iuſtified thy Sisters in all thine abominations which thou haſt done. Thou alſoe which haſt Iudged thy Siſters, beare thyne owne shame for thy ſins, that thou haſt committed <hi>more abominable then they:</hi> they are more righteous then thou: yea be thou confounded alſo, and bear they shame, in that thou haſt Iuſtified thy Siſters.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Matthew <hi>21:19.</hi>
               </bibl> And when <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſaw a fig tree in the way, he came to it, and found nothing thereon but leaves only, and ſaid unto it, let no fruit grow on thee hence forward for ever, And preſently the figtree withered away.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Proverbs <hi>27:6.</hi>
               </bibl> Faithfull are the wounds of a Freind: but the kiſes of an Enemie are deceitfull.</q>
            <p>Printed May 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:99537:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99537:2"/>
            <head>For his EXCELLENCY the Lord GENERAL CROMWELL theſe preſent in England.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is ſaid in Job the 35 and the 9 and 10 <hi>that by reaſon of the multitude of oppreſſions, they make the oppreſſed to cry: they cry out, by reaſon of the arme of the mighty, but none ſaith, where is God my maker, who gives ſongs in the night.</hi> And if this be my caſe in the higheſt, I know no man that can rationally blame me: <hi>If I cry out with all the shrillnes and loudnes I can.</hi> And that it is my caſe; my Lord, is evident, 1 In that I am banished for ever out of my Native Country and upon paine of death muſt be gone by ſuch a day, as appeares by your votes of the 15 of January laſt, recorded in my late <hi>Printed Apologie to the people of the Netherlands,</hi> page 48, 49, 50. 2ly You have made it death and loſs of Eſtate for any man whatever to afford me in England or its territories, for love or money, a nights lodgeing after that day, as appeares by your printed Act of the 30 of January laſt, recorded <hi>in the ſaid Apologie</hi> page 62, 63. 3ly All your ports were at that time with ſtrictnes ſtopt to prevent people from goeing out of England, without paſſes under the hand or hands of ſome in Authority; and yet. 4ly When according to your votes, I was willing to be gone and came to your ſpeaker for a paſs to inable me to goe, it was poſitively denied me by him, as I have truly related in the ſaid Apologie page 59. and the want of ſuch a paſs, in the eye of reaſon, had coſt me my life, had I not found favour at Dover, in the eyes of thoſe, whoſe faces before to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, I had never ſeene in my daies. And yet this is not all; for, beſides, I am fined ſeven-thouſand pound, which was more then viſibly I was worth. and, if it had bin immediately executed or leavyed, according to the ſeverity in your ſaid votes and Act, it had not left me a penny to hire an horſe to carry me to the ſea-ſide, no nor there to hire a boate to carry me on ship-board, nor there to give any recompence to the Maſter of the ship to carry me away to ſave my life; nay nor there to buy me a bit of victuals to ſuſteine life as I goe; nay nor when I am ſet ashore in a land of ſtrangers, to pay for one nights lodgeing for my refresh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Nay, that which is more then all this is, that there is not in any of your foreſaid votes or Act of Parliament, ſixpence proviſion made to buy bread to ſupport the lives of my poore wiſe and tender babes, although by Magna Charta chapter the 14 and the ſtatute of the 3 of Edward the 1 chap. 6, both which are lawes to this day unrepealed, &amp; they expreſly and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively ſay, <q>a freeman shall not be amerced for a ſmall fault, but after the manner of the fault and for a great fault after the greatnes thereof, ſaveing to him his continement</q> that is is to ſay <q>his freehold, countenance or <hi>livelyhood,</hi> and a merchant likewiſe ſaveing to him his merchandiſe, and a vilane, farmer, or husbandman ſaveing to him his waynage, or plough. And none of the ſaid amercements or ſines shall be aſſeſſed ſave by the oath of honeſt and lawfull men of the vicinage</q> that is to ſay JURIES. Nay and yet notwithſtanding all this, I have by your directions (for any thing I know to the contrary) given to your <hi>endeared and boſome agent</hi> MR. THOMAS SCOT, <hi>a ſpie clapt upon me at Dover,</hi> as I came over, called Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine WENDY OXFORD, who muſt ſtand upon the <hi>pillory at</hi> Weſtminſter and the exchange of London, and <hi>ſemingly</hi> be <hi>bannished</hi> from England the better to inable him undiſcerned to contrive my murder, ruine and diſtruction. whoſe <hi>roguery</hi> with <hi>Mr. Scots</hi> againſt me I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve infallibly found out from ſtep to ſtep, and by the aſſiſtance of God, as ſoone as I can ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve a little leaſure shall print it to publique vew. of which villany of his, when I gave him a hint of it, at my owne chamber, at or upon the 2 of Aprill laſt old Style, and by my letter to him dated the next day: with in 2 or 3 days after that he left Amſterdam, and departed with his two <hi>Gentil-women,</hi> called by him his <hi>wife</hi> and <hi>maide,</hi> although ſome doe with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence give very ſtrong reaſons to demonſtrate, they neither of them are ſuch, but a <hi>couple</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:99537:3"/>of <hi>arrant common whores.</hi> but averball hue and cry I then ſent after him, which I ſuppoſe with this, &amp;c. Will for ever ſpoile him of being <hi>a ſpy</hi> heere after (as well as ſomething elſe hath alredy ſpoyled <hi>Mr. Cheshire</hi> his brother <hi>knave,</hi> to be a ſpy at <hi>Middelborow</hi> who now is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to fly to Weſtminſter for Shelter) and render him uncapable to receive any more bills of exchange from Mr. <hi>Thomas Scot,</hi> for the paying him his ſallery, to inable him to <hi>drinke drunke night and day,</hi> to <hi>feaſt, whore it, ſwear, rant</hi> it and <hi>domineer</hi> rather like a <hi>bedlam</hi> then a man; or to ſend one of his <hi>ſluts</hi> over to give <hi>Mr. Scot</hi> if he want it a <hi>taſt</hi> of hir (which kind of <hi>flesh</hi> is notoriouſly at Weſtminſter knowne he <hi>loves</hi> as well as <hi>Oxford</hi> doth) as well as to convey his intelligence over and to ſolicet him, if he ly not in, <hi>ſicke of the French Pox</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him <hi>a paſſe</hi> to come over, and to meet him, at Graves-end or Dover, &amp;c. and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with him for ſetling all his affairs.</p>
            <p>And yet <hi>my Lord</hi> this is not all, but that which is the higheſt, of <hi>aggrevations</hi> is, that all this that is done unto me, (and <hi>principally by your ſelfe</hi>) is inflicted upon me, without (I doe avow it and upon my life dare ingage to make it good) all shaddow of ground, cauſe, provocation or cullour of law or Juſtice; For, alas <hi>my Lord,</hi> I was at moſt upon your owne principles, but an acceſſarie and not principal; And to inflict a higher and greater punishment upon me then upon Mr. <hi>Primat</hi> the <hi>principall,</hi> and now to ſet him at liberty from his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to keepe me ſtill in my <hi>banishment,</hi> and under the <hi>lash</hi> of my foreſaid <hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary great fine:</hi> where is in <hi>England</hi> either the <hi>Law, equity</hi> or <hi>juſtice,</hi> to avow and <hi>warrant it?</hi> And my LORD, admit <hi>Mr. Primates</hi> Petition about which I am <hi>banished,</hi> had bin all falſe, and not proved, <hi>(which yet I avow to the contrary)</hi> and admit, it conteines in it <hi>ſo high things againſt</hi> Sr. ARTHVR HASELRIGE, as if proved, would have occaſioned as great a ſentence to him, as you have given to me; and therefore <hi>per legem talionis</hi> you have done by me, as you have done. <hi>Truly</hi> MY LORD <hi>I will joyne yſsue with you there,</hi> if that be your ground, as by ſome of your members while I was in <hi>England,</hi> I underſtood, it was one of your <hi>principalleſt.</hi> Yet remember, you ſay in your Declarations, <q>that the Law of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is the Inheritance and birth-right of the MEANEST MAN therof</q> as well as <q>of the GREATEST, and that you are bound in duty and conſcience both to God and Man to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe it EQUALLY to all, WITHOUT FAVOUR OR AFFECTION:</q> and therfore be but juſt to me <hi>my Lord</hi> and I have done with you. For your <hi>Attorney Generall</hi> PRIDEAUX (<hi>that unbrac't Drum,</hi> that makes a great ſound &amp; noyſe, <hi>without any tune or harmony</hi>) accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; INDICTED <hi>me</hi> of <hi>high-treaſon,</hi> and had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tryed before <hi>about</hi> 40 <hi>judges at Guildhall London in October</hi> 1649 <hi>for my life therefore:</hi> and if he had proved it againſt me, I muſt have <hi>died therfore</hi> as a traytor, and have <hi>forfeited</hi> all my eſtate. And therfore by your owne ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le and your owne Law of proceedings with me in my preſent caſe; becauſe he accuſed me, &amp; could not prove it, „he ought to be hanged therefore, and to forfeit 4 parts of 7 of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate to me.„ which when I was at <hi>London</hi> by common repute, he was judged by his <hi>Land, Poſtmaſter-Generall-ship,</hi> attorney-<hi>Generall-ship</hi> and the moſt <hi>vaſt fees,</hi> that he [being a Parliament man OF AN UNACCOUNTABLE PARLIAMENT, and thereby ſo great) takes to plead all manner <hi>of baſe Cauſes,</hi> to the <hi>threatening,</hi> OUT FACEING &amp; <hi>overaweing</hi> both JUDGES, <hi>Iurors</hi> and <hi>Lawyers,</hi> to have incomeing thereby annually about <hi>twenty thouſand pounds.</hi> Although a few yeares agoe, ſince this <hi>eternall Parliaments</hi> firſt ſitting, I could never heare he was judged to be worth two hundred Pounds per annum.</p>
            <p>Now, I ſay my <hi>Lord,</hi> performe this to me, &amp; I will pay you my <hi>ſeven-thouſand-pound fine,</hi> without any more to doe. But beſides, remember alſo, were not you <hi>(My Lord)</hi> at <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by-houſe in Cheynel-row</hi> with the Councel of State, upon the 28 of March 1649, the <hi>cheife man</hi> to mannage an <hi>accuſation of high-treaſon againſt me,</hi> and got me committed therefore. The Narrative of which in breife, is <hi>conteined</hi> in the 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, pages of the <hi>ſecond edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99537:3"/>of the <hi>Picture of the Councel of State,</hi> printed at London 1649. and yet when it came to the yſſue, there could never one word of it be proved, all though I lay priſoner in the Tower, almoſt a yeare there upon, and therfore by your owne rule and law of proceedings with me, <hi>ought not you your ſelfe [my Lord] to be HANGED therefore?</hi> and to forfeit 4 parts of ſeven of your great eſtate to me therefore? For shame my LORD, <hi>once in your life, learne to be juſt</hi> and remember what you ſaid againſt <hi>Mr. Herbert, the Kings attorney Generall,</hi> in the Caſe of the LORD KIMBOLTON and the 5 MEMBERS 1 part of the booke of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Declarations page 52, 53, 101, 123, 201, 203, 208, 210, 278, 459, 660: and give me not too much cauſe to <hi>picture-draw you ſo,</hi> that all the <hi>artificial</hi> or <hi>penſil-limners</hi> in the world, SHALL NOT BE ABLE TO COMPARE WITH IT. You know, I have a quick &amp; sharpe pen <hi>(My Lord)</hi> and therefore give me not cauſe to <hi>challenge you,</hi> or any of your Champions, to draw into a <hi>short Epitomy,</hi> or into a <hi>larger charge,</hi> all that evill that in your owne thoughts you can colourably imagine the <hi>Buyshops, Starr-chamber, Counſell-table, High-commisſion,</hi> or any perſons therein were <hi>guilty</hi> of; nay or any perſons ſince their downe-fall by you exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for the <hi>higheſt of treaſons, tyrannyes</hi> &amp; <hi>oppresſions</hi> were guilty of: &amp; yet, <hi>comparatis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parandis,</hi> for me to aver that you outſtrip them all, and in particulars to undertake upon my life to make it good: and that thoſe ſayings of God, by the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> chap: 16, 48, 51, 52, <hi>[mentioned on the Title-page)</hi> may as truly and as juſtly be verified of you, as they were of <hi>Iudah or Ieruſalem</hi> &amp; that you have outſtrip't <hi>(comparatis comparandis)</hi> all thoſe whome you your ſelfe count the moſt wicked men, that you have pulled downe, „and thereby have done in actions as much as in you lies, to juſtifie all their wickednes„ that in words you have condemned. And beſides, <hi>my Lord,</hi> what faith, what truth, what honeſty? can be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be in that man, or that generation of men? that by a conſtant ſeries of his or their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, viſiby and apparently declare, <q>he or they hold it lawfull to commit any manner of wickednes &amp; baſenes whatſoever that can be named under the ſunn, for the accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his or their propoſed end</q> whether in it ſelfe, it be wicked or righteous: yea to <hi>cheat, breake faith with,</hi> and murther the nigheſt relations a man can converſe with, when they croſs his ends.</p>
            <p>Yea &amp; for that end onely, to raiſe warrs upon warrs, to the devaſtation of Kingdomes &amp; Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; The gulled, cheated &amp; abuſed peoples lives, really &amp; truly being of no more value with him or them, then ſo many dead doggs, ſerving him or them for no other end, but to be his <q>foote-ſteps to climbe up to the top of abſolute and arbitrary Power &amp; pretended Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</q> 
               <hi>or unlimited &amp; unbounded Kingship.</hi> And, that you <hi>(my Lord)</hi> particularly are the man, that is guiltie of all this, in my judgement and apprehenſion, your owne quondam darling, „and heart-indeared &amp; heart ſecret-knowing Freind, <hi>the Major of your owne Regiment of Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, Robert Huntington</hi>„ in his printed <hi>impeachment</hi> of you, delivered to both houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt you, the 2 of Auguſt 1648, <hi>hath punctually declared it,</hi> which <hi>impeachment,</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in the 53, 54, 55, 56, 57, 58, 59, 60 &amp; 61 pages of that Booke for makeing of which I was arraigned for a Traitor at <hi>Guildhall</hi> October 1649, being intituled <hi>An Impeachment of high-Treaſon against Oliver Cromwell, &amp;c.</hi> and for which <hi>Impeachment</hi> of his, I could never heare, that you endeavoured ſo much as publicly to queſtion, him therfore, or to put forth a <hi>vindication</hi> againſt it. Which may well get beleife in <hi>un-biaſed</hi> men, that you acknowledge <hi>all that he hath there ſaid againſt you, to be true.</hi> And as much as I have ſaid of him, and his <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment,</hi> may be ſaid of the <hi>Authors</hi> of thoſe thre notable bookes and of the bookes themſelves called PUTNEY-PROIECTS; The LEVELLERS <hi>vindicated, being the ſtated caſe, of the late</hi> TREACHEROUSLY <hi>defeated</hi> BVRFORD-<hi>troopes;</hi> and the HVE-AND-CRIE <hi>of the young men &amp; apprentiſes of London after the loſt fundamentall laws &amp; liberties of England.</hi> Vnto which three bookes, a great many mens names are ſet, <hi>as the avowers &amp; juſtifiers of them,</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99537:4"/>to my knowledge, the moſt of their names are true: for I particularly know the moſt of the men my ſelfe, &amp; yet I could never heare that any one of them, <hi>was ſo much as queſtioned for decyfering you there, as they have done.</hi> Although to my knowledge, <hi>you know</hi> ſome of the men as well as I doe, and might ſeverall times ſince <hi>thoſe bookes were writ &amp; published,</hi> as eaſily have laid your hands upon them, to have called them to <hi>an account therefore,</hi> as I can take up the pen &amp; inke that I write here with.</p>
            <p>I ſay, laying the forementioned <hi>Bookes</hi> or diſcourſes together, with what followes in this diſcourſe page 13, 14, 15, to 24 &amp; compareing them with <hi>your practiſe,</hi> I thinke they ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently prove you to be the man above mentioned, that walks by the <hi>Principles of</hi> ATHEISME &amp; MACHIAVELLSME, <hi>and holds it lawful to doe any thing in the world that comes in your way, that will moſt ſerve your</hi> turne, for the accomplishment of your owne ends, be they never ſo <hi>bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, wicked, or tyrannicall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But MY LORD you have forced me when I was quiet, to come upon the ſtage agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne much againſt my will and ſtudious indeavours. And yet, when I did, I fairely ſought pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce with you, and ſent you in writeing <hi>my propoſitions for peace,</hi> grounded only upon your <hi>owne promiſes,</hi> neglecting to inſiſt upon any thing of concernement to my ſelfe. and gave you, or your true Freind <hi>Mr. William Kiffen,</hi> to whom I ſent it, <hi>twentie one dayes,</hi> to returne me an anſwer, at leaſt of his receit thereof; all which appeares in the following diſcourſe page 29, 30, 31. But heareing nothing at all from him and feareing that it is intecepted, I am forced to print it. The Copie whereof, with ſome ſmall additions, thus followeth.</p>
            <trailer>For my loveing Freind Mr. WILLIAM KIFFIN, <hi>merchant at his Houſe in Dukes-place London, theſe with haſt, poſt haſt, to be communicated to his Excellency the Lord Generall Cromwell, &amp;c.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99537:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. KIFFIN.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu and I have bin long acquainted a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d have had much converſe together &amp; although you were in my late troubles before my triall at <hi>GVILD-HALL</hi> my adverſary in print; yet not lookeing upon you by your oppoſition, as a man that out of malice deſignedly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to take away my life, <hi>but rather at a man ſurpriſed in your underſtanding,</hi> and thereby induced to beleive the plauſible arguments of my <hi>(pretended Religious)</hi> adverſaries, as though by my conteſt with them, an undeniable gap was opened, to let in them that are commonly called the public adverſaries to devoure all: and ſo were againſt the then ſeaſon <hi>as unfit and dangerous</hi> in your apprehenſion, but not againſt the things themſelves held forth by me and my Camerades, <hi>which you judged juſt and righteous</hi> and ſit to be eſtablished in due time, when that feare was over. In which regard that oppoſition of yours to me, I judged moſt fit to be buryed in the grave, <hi>and not with any diſgust of mind to be remembred.</hi> And therfore it is that of late, ſome part of that former familiarity that was betwixt us, hath bin renewed and ſince my banishment I find by ſeveral Letters from my wife, that you have bin very civil and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectfull to her, <hi>for which I returne you many (AND MY HE ARTIEST) thankes. ONE OF HER LETTERS dated the</hi> 2. <hi>of Feb: laſt I have anſwered in print, and cauſed that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to be published here as well</hi> in <hi>DVTCH</hi> as <hi>ENGLISH;</hi> which I hope before the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te herof is <hi>reprinted at London</hi> againe, ſince which I have received <hi>two Letters more from</hi> her, the maine ſubſtance of both of which are, <hi>to preſume, with all the mournfull arguments that pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly thee can uſe, to be quiet and to abſtaine from printing,</hi> and Withall she tells me, <hi>it is the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of all my Freindes in generall who come continually to her, to gather to write to me about it.</hi> But haveing in my aforeſaid printed Epiſtle, given her undeniable reaſons <hi>WHY I AM COMPELLED TO PRINT,</hi> which I hope with my former Letters to her, will ſo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie and ſeaſon her Spirit, that I may preſume now, that both my feares are over, which were <hi>firſt, that I was afraid through ſorrow about me and her owne diſtreſſed condition</hi> [as she calls it) <hi>the should either miſcarry of her childe,</hi> or elſe ſecondly <hi>that she should be overwhelmed with greife and ſo her burthen should become too heavie for her to beare.</hi> But hopeing that both of theſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are over, I muſt now confeſs unto you, that that little trouble which uſed formerly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company me, thorough the hopes hereof is as good as at an end. And therfore to you shall I judge it convenient for me, [<hi>and</hi> 1 <hi>hope no way miſchevous to your ſelfe</hi>] to anſwer freindly and reſolutely ſome other clauſes in her latter Letters, and ſome clauſes in other Letters of ſome of my Freindes, which I have lately received, and <hi>then poſitively to tell you without deceit or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery my future reſolutions,</hi> [by the aſſiſtance of God] on purpoſe becauſe I know you are great with the <hi>GENERALL</hi> and I thinke with the <hi>NOW LORD-DEPVTY OF YRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND LAMBERT,</hi> but I am ſure of it, with <hi>LENTENANT-GENERALL FLEETWOOD</hi> and <hi>MAIOR-GENERALL HARRISON</hi> that you may shew this Letter unto them all, being the great ſword men of England, that ſo they may lay their heads together obout it, (if they pleaſe) and then let God worke his pleaſure</p>
            <p>In a large Letter to my wiſe of the 13 <hi>of February</hi> laſt, I told her, and now with comfort and rejoiceing tell you, <hi>that I bleſs God, that I have this teſtimony in mine owne Conſcience; that the Cauſe for mannageing of which I am bannished, did at the firſt and all along to this very houre doth appeare to my underſtanding &amp; judgement, upon the ſtricteſt ſcrutinie betwixt God and mine owne ſoule, that I am able to make, to be as righteous and as just a cauſe, as ever was in the World, and all ſo however</hi> Mr. HILL THE CHAIR-MAN <hi>reported it to the houſe, yet</hi> Mr. PRIMATES PETITION <hi>was as fully proved, before him and the Committee of Parliament in every circumſtance of it, ſo far as its capable of proofe, [ſaveing that ſingle clauſe of SIR AR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THVR HASILRIGS holding private correſpondence, with ſome of the Commisſioners,] as any puition in the world need to be proved, but it was no wonder it went as it did, when SIR AR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THVR
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99537:5"/>HASILRIG WITH Mr. HIL THE CHAIRMAN, WITHOVT A THIRD MAN, DREW VP THE GREATEST PART OF THE REPORT, IN THE SPEAKERS CHAMBER, WHILE THE HOVSE WAS SIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TING, as one that tooke them at it told we with his owne tongue. Which report we were never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſee, nor none for us, nor to heare red, although we earneſtly intreated for it, and by importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity endeavoured it. And beſides I am confident of it there was not three men, that judged the cauſe in the Houſe, that ever at the Committee, were conſtant hearers of it from the beginning to the end. And by what I have heard from Parliament men, that were at the Committee ſeverall daies, Mr. HILL NEVER REPORTED TO THE HOVSE, ONE TENTH PART OF OVR EVIDENCES AS WEE LAID THEM DOWNE BEFORE THE COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MITTEE, AND THE SAID Mr. HILL WAS OPENLY IN THE HOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SE TAXED WITH SEVERALL MATERIALL OMISSIONS, BY A PERSON OR PERSONS THAT HEARD NOT ONE HALFE OF IT AT THE COMMITTEE. And beſides, when the GENERALL HIMSELFE ſet his shoulders to the worke, with all the might he had in the World, to have the ſentence ſo paſs and goe on, it is unimaginable it could goe otherwiſe then it did, for one</hi> THAT IS FAMILIAR WITH HIM AND THAT WISHETH ME WELL, TOLD ME, IT WAS IN THE GE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NERALLS HOVSE BY HIM AND A CABAL OF PARLIAMENT MEN A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GREED OF, TWO OR THREE DAIES, BEFORE IT WAS VOTED OR DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CLARED IN THE PARLIAMENT. <hi>And ſome dayes after it was paſsed, the</hi> GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RALL HIMSELFE IN THE OPEN HOVSE <hi>(as one that heard him told me)</hi> IN A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SPEECH OF HIS DID AVERR AND DECLARE VPON HIS CONSCIENCE, THAT THE SENTENCE IT SELFE PASSED AGAINST ME, WAS AS HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEST AND AS JVST A SENTENCE, AS WAS EVER PASSED BY THAT HOVSE. <hi>But I doubt not (through the asſiſtance of God) in a short time, to make it clearly and evidently to appeare in every circumſtance, that it is the</hi> MOST VNJVST, ILLEGAL AND VNRIGHTEOVS SENTENCE, THAT EVER WAS <hi>paſſed by any authority or power in the World, that ever profeſſed to governe by Lawe, As in abundance of their declarations, they have profeſſed before God and the World, they ought and would doe. But at the preſent, I shall only trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with one inſtance and that in a short Declaration of theirs intitled, a Declaration of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of England for maintainning the fundamental Lawes of this Nation,</hi> dated Feb. 9. 1648. made by them ſince they tooke of the Kings head declaredly for Tyrannie, Oppresſion and and exerciſeing an Arbitrary power in which they poſitively declare, <hi>that they are fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to maintaine &amp; shall &amp; will uphold, preſerve and keepe, the fundamentale Lawes of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for and concerning the preſervation of the lives, properties and Liberties of the people, with all things incident thereunto, with the alterations touching Kings and Houſe of Lords, allready reſolved in this preſent Parliament for the good of the People.</hi> Which short declaration of theirs, is fully backed by them with a larger delaration, made the 17 of March after. <hi>And although, there be an abſolute neceſſity that lies upon me, as ſpeedily as I can to goe to the preſs with ſuch a thing; yet in what I write or print by the aſsiſtance of God all mighty, I shall keepe within the bounds of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, THAT VALVES HIS PEACE WITH GOD ABOVE ALL EAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THLY TREASVRES IN THE WORLD, and of a rationall man,</hi> THAT HATH PRINCIPLES OF FREEDOME AND JVSTICE INGRAFTED IN HIM, THAT HE WILL NOT BALKE OR CHANGE FOR ALL THE FEARES OF ALL THE DEATHS IN THE EARTH; and of an English-man, <hi>THAT LOVES HIS NATIVE COVNTRIE ABOVE ALL OTHER COVNTRIES IN THE WORLD, and in a great meaſure, hath the ſenſe of his duty in acting towards its Freedome and wellfare, INGRAVEN VPON HIS VERY HEART;</hi> and as a diſcreet man,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99537:5"/>THAT WILL NOT MEDDLE WITH THE NATIONS AFFAIRES OR GOVERNMENT WHERE HE SOIOURNES, OR DOE ANY THING TO THE UTMOST OF HIS POWER, THAT MAY GIVE THE LEAST DISCONTENT, TO THOSE MAGISTRATES UNDER WHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SE PROTECTION IN HIS BANNISHMENT HE LIVES. <hi>And beſides, I bleſs God, I have both publicly and privately walked, in all peace quietues and uprigtnes towards the General and Parliament ſince I owned their authority, and neither directly nor indirestly medled with them, to give them the leaſt offence, or to occaſion in them the leaſt cauſe of jealouſy of me for undermineing or endeavouring to undermine their power and authority, and therfore can I the more glorie and rejoyce under their harsh and cruell dealeing with me.</hi> BUT THE LORD IS RIGHTOUS, AND I AM CONFIDENT WILL SPEEDILY RETURNE IT SEVENFOLD INTO THE BOSOMES of thoſe who were the principal cauſers of it Judges: 1:6:7: and 2 Sam: 21, 1:2:5, 6:14: and 2 Sam: 12:31: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the 11: of Judges 17:18:19:20:23:27: Eſter 7:9:10: and 8:11. and 9:2:3:4:5:15. Iſaiah: 10:12:13:18. Mat: 7:2. Marke: 4:24. Luke 6:37:38. Rom: 2:3. Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes: 2:12. Revelations: 18:6:7:8.</p>
            <p>But to returne back; by my wives Letters I perceive, the LORD GENERALL <hi>gives a verie unworthy and ſtrange kind of character of me,</hi> which ſeemes to worke beleife upon the Spirits of ſome of my Freinds; and further ſaith, <hi>that I may thinke my ſentence greater then my offence, if they did not feare other things by me,</hi> of which alſo it ſeemes ſome of my Freinds are ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to all which; I ſay, its true upon the 28 <hi>of March</hi> 1649 <hi>the preſent Lord Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> cauſed me to be fetched out of my bed by a multitude of armed horſe and foote and got me ſent to the tower for a traitor, yet when I came to my triall for my life, there was never any thing of that laid unto my charge for which at firſt I was impriſoned, but only actions pretended to be done by me many moneths after my impriſonment, when I lay under ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny barbarous provocations, put upon me by the <hi>Generall and his confederates, AS HAD BIN SVFFICIENT</hi> (according to Solomons ſaying) <hi>TO MAKE A WISE MAN MAD.</hi> But how juſt it was to goe about to take away my life, upon that ſcore, I leave you to judge.</p>
            <p>Its alſo true. <hi>I am now banished by the GENERALL HIS MEANES</hi> and the public pretended grounds and reaſons therof are contained in the <hi>Parliaments printed Narrative and Act paſſed againſt me</hi> recorded in the 49: 50: 51: 62: 63 pages: of my late Apoligy to the people of the netherlands and I am ſure of it in both of them they lay no crime at all in Law unto my charge; as I have allready fully proved in my ſaid printed Apologie to the people of the Netherlands page: 65: 66: 67. But if the GENERALL OR ANY OTHER FOR HIM have any thing in imagination feare or ſuppoſition to lay to my charge, let him or them ſtand up and ſay their utmoſt, I crave no favour at their hands; but yet I appeale to your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, how juſt it is, <hi>to disfranchiſe a man of all his birthrights and bannish him forever out of his native Contrie, for things they feare he will act againſt them.</hi> Its confeſt, the GENERALL muſt now needs have ſomething to ſay for himſelfe againſt me, as well as his or HASILRIGGS AGENTS in times by-paſt had: who a little before my tryall at GUILDHALL <hi>Octob.</hi> 1649, <hi>in their</hi> printed Bookes againſt me, clothed me in beares and Wolves skins, that ſo the people as their doggs might worry me without compasſion or conſideration. And therfore it was <hi>that they printed me to be an Atheiſt, a denier of God and the Scripture &amp; given up to all licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and an abſolute confederate with Prince Charles,</hi> to ſet up his abſolute will &amp; prerogative in the English Nation. All or any of which things they them ſelves knew to be as true, as the ſea burnt. But read my Anſwer thereto <hi>Printed at the Latter end of the firſt part of my tryall at Guildhall, page</hi> 158, 159.</p>
            <p>Its alſo true, my old Freind Mr. CORNELIUS HOLLAND a little before my ſecond tryall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verred
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99537:6"/>to my wife, <hi>that at the Counſel of State they had Letters of mine under mine owne hand written to the Prince; and the LORD BRADSHAW did the ſame,</hi> to ſome eminent Freinds of mine. but when I bid defiance to them, and challenged them to produce them they were not albe to doe it, and it proved no more then ſome of Mr. THOMAS SCOTS ROTTEN AND POCKIE LIES.</p>
            <p>Its alſo true, that when I was tried for my life at <hi>GVILDHALL,</hi> and confidently and juſtly alleadged for my ſelfe <hi>that by the two ſtatutes of the firſt of Edward the ſixt Chapter the</hi> 12 <hi>and the</hi> 5 <hi>and</hi> 6 <hi>of Edward the</hi> 6 <hi>Chapter the</hi> 11 <hi>ſtill in force, there ought to bee two direct &amp; plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne evidences or witneſſes to prove every fact of treaſon alleadged againſt me:</hi> Yet thoſe two worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and bloody fellowes ATTORNY GENERALL PRIDEAUX and the LORD KEEBLE, could and did falſely and lieingly (not haveing the leaſt graine of the feare of God or common-honeſty or shame before their eyes) averre, <hi>that there was a ſtatute made after them in the</hi> 1 <hi>and</hi> 2 <hi>of Q. Mary</hi> that overthrew and abolished thoſe two forementioned ſtatutes <hi>of Edward the</hi> 6: <hi>and that now, one witnes to prove the treaſon alleaged against me, was ſufficient to take away my life.</hi> and this they averred againe and againe unto the jurie upon their reputations to be true, after that I had often before the Jury, and all the populous auditory that then was preſent, to their faces told them, <hi>it was falſe and untrue,</hi> and that there was no ſuch law made in Queen Maries time, <hi>and holding the ſtatute booke in mine hand, I challenged them againe and agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to name the Chapter that it might be read, the</hi> which they could not doe and yet like moſt bloodie and falſe men, <hi>they would have taken away my life by their lies, if I had not underſtood the Law as well as themſelves and had not had</hi> CONFIDENCE ENOUGH TO HAVE TOLD THEM THEY LIED TO THEIR FACES, before the jury and all that great auditorie of People, all which you may fully read at large <hi>in the firſt part of the booke of my triall page</hi> 124, 125, 141, 142, 143, 147.</p>
            <p>Now I ſay, laying all theſe things together, and <hi>conſidering that theſe three baſe unworthy men,</hi> are ſtill as great with the Generall as ever they were; I doe not wonder, if he have relations enough at his fingers end to make me odious. But upon what foundation or botto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, they should be grounded, <hi>(ſeeing mine owne Conſcience is clare and innocent)</hi> I cannot imagine; unleſs it be ſomething in relation to that averment, of Mr. REYNOLDS <hi>the ſollicitor Generall,</hi> who lately <hi>at a Committee of Parliament</hi> (as by a Letter from London I am informed) <hi>openly averred, I held correſpondency with the Scottish King;</hi> but whether he charged it upon me as done by me before my banishment, or ſince, the letter doth not declare. And therfore at preſent I can anſwer it but by Gueſs; and ſay,</p>
            <p>I beleive my adverſaries have ſome pangs of Conſcience in them (<q>For I am confident the wickedeſt and moſt ſeared Atheiſt or machiavel, or doer of deſpight unto the Spirit of grace in the World is not totally without them</q>) that now and them pricks them, as it <q>did profane Eſau, who for one morſell of meat ſold his birth-right, and afterward when he would have inherited the bleſſing was rejected and found no place of repentance though he ſought it carefully with teares <bibl>Heb: 12, 17.</bibl>
               </q> the ſame may be ſaid of wicked <hi>Cain and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Iudas</hi>) for that injuſtice which they have done unto me in banishing me without a Cauſe, and thereby, as much as in them lies; not only deſtroying of me, <hi>but alſo of my poore wife and harmeles babes.</hi> Which crueltie of theirs, it may be, either flies in their faces, <q>[for if wee ſinn willfully after we have received the knowledge of the truth, there remaines no more ſacrifice for sin, but a certaine fearfull lookeing for of judgment and fiery indignation, which shall devoure the adverſaries and it is a fearfull and dreadfull thing to fall (in wrath) into the hands of the liveing God <bibl>Heb. 10.26, 27, 31.</bibl>
               </q> Or they feare may be much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and laid to heart, (as I know it is) by the People of England of all ſorts, who in time it may be may make ſome of them ſmart for their unjuſt and barbarous dealeing with me.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99537:6"/>For ſaith the preſent Lord cheife Juſtice St. John, in his Argument of late againſt the Earle of Strafford printed and published by the ſpeciall order of the houſe of Commons in the year 1641: pag. 43, <hi>he that would not have others to have law, why should he have any himſelfe, why should not that be done to him, that his ſelfe would have done to others? It's true</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve law to hares,</hi> and deers, becauſe they be beaſts of chaſe, it was never <hi>accounted either cruelty or foule play to knock foxes and wolves on the head, as they can be found, becauſe theſe be beaſts of pray:</hi> And it is a righteous and juſt thing both in the ſight of God and man, <hi>to meaſure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them as they have meaſured unto others,</hi> Judges 1:6:7. Matth: 7:2 Marke 4:24. Luke 6:37:38. Rom: 2:1. and therfore upon the Principles of Machiavel, <hi>they count it neceſsary to beſpatter me and load me with that,</hi> which though in it ſelfe never ſo falſe, yet they beleive and hope may make me looſe mine Intereſt in England, which I have in the affections of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of mine honeſt and indeared Freinds there. Who I know doe looke upon me, as a <hi>ſingle-hearted, honeſt, juſt, plaine-ſpoken English-man, that hath bin valiaunt and couragious for the regaining</hi> and preſerveing their Freedomes and liberties, though accompanied with frailties and infirmities, which all, yea the beſt of the ſonns of men are ſubject to. And if they could make me looſe mine Intereſt with mine honeſt Freinds; I were then but ſingle <hi>Iohn Lilburne</hi> nothing at all conſiderable either to be loved or feared. in hopes and confidence to preſerve which, I further ſay; If Mr. REYNOLDS by my correſponding with the Prince, meane that I did it at any time in the leaſt before I was banished; I bid defiance to him, and challenge him, to inſtance if he can, averring that his accuſation is moſt falſe.</p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, if he meane, that I have <hi>correſponded</hi> with him ſince I was <hi>bannished,</hi> then I deſire him to explaine what he <hi>calls correſponding,</hi> or elſe I know not fully how to anſwer him. But this at preſent I shall ſay, and that in truth and faithfullnes as before the Lord all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, that knowes my heart and beares witnes to me that I lie not, <hi>that ſince the day the Parliament voted my bannishment,</hi> I have neither writ Letter line or ſillabe to the <hi>Prince</hi> or any about him, nor received Letter, line or ſillabe from him or any about him. Neither <hi>have I dicttated any Letter</hi> or any part of a <hi>Letter</hi> to him or any about him, or <hi>appertaineing</hi> to him. Neither have I heard any <hi>Letter</hi> red to this very houre, that hath bin <hi>writt,</hi> or <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended</hi> to be <hi>writt</hi> to him or any about him.</p>
            <p>Its true, ſince I came to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> I have bin very much threatened by ſome of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſort of the Cavaliers; <hi>firſt by three of them,</hi> that came to the lodgeing where I lay the firſt night, where they were very <hi>uncivil and debaucht,</hi> as I am informed, and very probably might have done me a miſcheif had I then bin there. and ſecondly, ſince that, one more of them, hath to ſome <hi>English people</hi> whom I have cauſe to truſt, <hi>threatened to ruine and deſtroy me,</hi> and others of them, and they of ſome port and quality, in the preſence of ſome that are no mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ones, and that I know love me intirely, <hi>have ſworne within theſe few daies moſt bitterly, that I am a ſpie from</hi> CROMWELL <hi>and a rogue that deſerve to be knockt on the head.</hi> Laying all which together and thoſe many and ſtrong invitations, that I have had to come into ſome of their companies, I have judged the hand and finger of MR. THOMAS SCOT, <hi>that fellow all moſt ſtarke rotten with the French-po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and ſome of his agents</hi> or ſpies, have abſolutely <hi>bin at the botto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of this,</hi> which to me appears thus. I know my walkings, as to man, are and have bin ſo upright and juſt (as to man) that all my <hi>adverſaries</hi> in England are not able to <hi>blemish them,</hi> and I beleive my adverſaries know as much, <hi>being I know they have allready ſearched as with a candle into the bottome and ſecreteſt of my actions and wayes;</hi> and therfore know, that unleſs they can in the thoughts of my Freinds blemish me, in reference to the <hi>Prince,</hi> whom they have <hi>declared a traitor</hi> and therfore would be glad they had the leaſt ground in the world to averre me to my Freinds to be <hi>apoſtatiſed</hi> from my principles, by <hi>correſponding</hi> with him or his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, knowing they can have no plauſible way in their owne thoughts to keepe my <hi>darts</hi> of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99537:7"/>from them, and to diſenable me to worke out mine owne <hi>reſtauration</hi> to the full enjoyment of my <hi>native English birth rights,</hi> but this. For if they could but colourably hold out this, they would caſily by virtue of ſeverall of their acts, <hi>declare all thoſe traitors that write but a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to me, or receive but a Letter from me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therfore I beleive MR. SCOT hath by ſpeciall inſtructions from HIS MASTER THE GENERALL, ordered ſome of his ſpies, that lie in the boſome of the <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> to provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke them to ſpeake big words againſt me, <hi>yea and it may be to endeavour to take away my life,</hi> on purpoſe to neceſſitate me through feare to keepe company with them, and to grow fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar with them, that ſo they might have ſome ground to write over to him thereof, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by erne their promiſed ſalary from him, <hi>and write their ſecrets to him betwixt their inkie lines ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with</hi> SACK <hi>or the</hi> JUICE OF A LIMON (according to his common inſtructions) <hi>which by holding betwixt him &amp; the</hi> FIRE, <hi>he can eaſily read, although a ſtranger that should intercept his Letters</hi> (AS PERADVENTURE I OR SOME FOR ME HAVE ALLREADY DONE) that knows not his devices, could not doe it.</p>
            <p>But Sir, not to put a cloake upon things, I'll deale plainly and freely with you. I judgeing there was and is ſuch a <hi>designe</hi> upon me as is before <hi>expreſſed,</hi> and haveing many invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to talke with ſome of the <hi>Kings partie;</hi> leaſt a <hi>conſtant deniall</hi> ſo to doe, should give cauſe to them to <hi>conclude</hi> and judge me <hi>infallibly</hi> to be a <hi>ſpie indeed,</hi> or to be as baſe and vile as ſome of them doe imagine me to bee, therfore in order to mine owne <hi>preſervation</hi> and that I might not be intrapped nor <hi>destroid,</hi> before I did that in reference to my <hi>bannish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that my <hi>braine</hi> hath allready <hi>modelliſed</hi> unto my ſelfe, <q>I have beene of late in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of their companies and talked my mind rationally and freely to them, in juſtification of MINE OWNE PRINCIPLES;</q> and I am conſident of it, have made as much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to my ſelfe of their diſcourſes with me, as any of them can doe of mine. And I muſt conſeſs unto you, had I bin formerley addicted to ſet up the <hi>preſent Scottiſh Kings Intereſt,</hi> yet by my diſcourſeing with them, I did find ſo much ground and reaſon, <hi>as quite to diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi> me for the future, ſo much as to thinke of any ſuch thing, in their way.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe <hi>I find the KING</hi> by their diſcourſe, although a man judged by them of parts, yet is he not of that Depth of judgement and ſoliditie, as that he <hi>dare truſt</hi> his owne judgement and underſtanding, <hi>in the mannagement of any great deſigne.</hi> And I am confident that if he truſt to the <hi>multitude</hi> of his Councellours, there are ſome of them men that will talke their minds freely, (eſpecially to company in a <hi>Taverne,</hi>) by meanes of which it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible <hi>but the Parliaments gold and ſilver,</hi> with the helpe of MR. THOMAS SCOTS <q>agents or ſpies, which he hath in all Nations of Europe (BUT ESPECIALLY NEARE UNTO THE PRINCE) by their intelligence will be to hard for them all, and therby know the bottome of their greateſt deſignes, before they be a quarter ripe for execution.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe, by my diſcourſe with ſome of them I find, that not only the <hi>Prince himſelfe,</hi> but his cheiſeſt Councellours, are for his comeing in by <hi>force and conqueſt;</hi> which is a principle I as much hate as any man in the World doth: and have <hi>given as cleare teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> againſt ſuch a Principle and <hi>practiſe</hi> in any perſon what ſoever as any man <hi>upon the face of the earth ever did or durſt doe, I am confident of it.</hi> But beſides; I have profeſſed to be a <hi>man of Conſcience</hi> and one that could <hi>die</hi> for his <hi>principles</hi> and never could be threatned from them, <hi>nor courted out of them, by anie perſons in the World what ſoever.</hi> And it hath bin one of my maine principles, and ſo declared by the <hi>conſtant ſeries</hi> of my practiſe, <hi>that evil muſt not be done by any, that good may come thereby.</hi> The Apoſtle by the Spirit of God, <hi>haveing concluded the damnation of ſach practiſers to be juſt,</hi> Romanes 3, 8. but if I should out of <hi>Machiavel</hi> or any other <hi>Politic Author</hi> learne ſuch Principles, as to joine with the <hi>Prince</hi> or any other Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt whatſoever, out of a deſigne of being revenged of my adverſaries, <hi>to conquer the People
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99537:7"/>of England, that</hi> therby he or any elſe might rule over them by his will and pleaſure: I should not only account my ſelfe, <hi>one of the greateſt murtherers in the World</hi> but alſo one of the <hi>baſeſt fellowes</hi> that ever breathed upon the face of the earth. Knowing very well: <hi>that none is to rule over the ſonns of men by will and pleaſure but God only and alone.</hi> But truly, I am afraid my LORD GENERALL CROMWELL HIMSELFE hath really that <hi>latitude</hi> in his <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> that will eaſily lead him out and permit him to act ſuch a practiſe, <hi>as I dare pawne my head,</hi> by his actions for many yeares together, clearly to evince and Manifeſt. And it may without <hi>a ſpeedy reconciliation</hi> in short time prove the ſubject of my pen. And therfore he haveing ſuch Principles within himſelfe, may judge thereby that I have the like, and thereby may be left to as large an elbow-roome as himſelfe takes.</p>
            <p>But for diſputacions ſake, <hi>at preſent, admit that I am</hi> ſo. Yet truly I muſt tell you, I have <hi>red Machiavil</hi> and the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and of <hi>Iudah</hi> contained in the Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and many other Hiſtories and alſo within this 15 yeares have ſeene aboundance of expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rince even in England it ſelfe; out of all which I cannot ſee the leaſt ground to draw any manner of inference, to induce me to ſide with a man or Intereſt of men, <hi>that are beaten out of all,</hi> and totally to forſake mine owne Intereſt among thoſe, that live under thoſe, <hi>that are in poſſeſion of all manner of power and ſtrength;</hi> or to thinke that ever by a <hi>forreign Arme</hi> or power of force, he can ever probably overturne them. Eſpecially conſidering experience teacheth me, aſſuredly to knowe that his bare attempting and endeavouring of it, <hi>joines them in England all together in one against him; although in many other things they are much divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves.</hi> I am ſure of it in Scripture I read, that when <hi>Abſalom</hi> had a mind to be <hi>King</hi> of Iſrael, he did not preſently goe about to raiſe force to obtaine it, although he nor none of his intereſt were ever beaten before, <hi>but he courted the People and ſtole away their hearts, by obſerveing to them his Fathers negligence to doe the people right, when they came to complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and handſomely reproveing</hi> of it in him, by telling the People <hi>there was no man deputed by the King to heare them: and therfore before</hi> the People he wished O THAT HE WERE MADE A JUDGE IN THE LAND, <hi>that every man that had a ſuit or cauſe might come unto him, and he would doe them juſtice;</hi> and when any man came nigh to doe him obeyſance, <hi>he comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented to the purpoſe with them, and put forth his hand and tooke them and kiſſed them:</hi> by meanes of which he <hi>rivetted</hi> himſelfe in the <hi>Peoples</hi> hearts and <hi>affections:</hi> and in proceſs of time therby he made his Father <hi>King David to flie before him,</hi> 2 Sam: 15:1, 2, 3, 4, &amp;c. So likewiſe JEHV for his owne ends, could cry out, <hi>come with me and ſee my zeale for the Lord</hi> 2 Kings 10, 16.</p>
            <p>And as I have red the <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſo I have ſeene much experience in <hi>England,</hi> and firſt, I have obſerved the Parliament by their <hi>curious oylie and ſweet declarations</hi> in reference to the People <hi>out-courted and out bid the King</hi> (who in his, ſtood upon the <hi>punctillioes of his preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi>) and therby <hi>won</hi> the hearts of the people from him, which proved his ruine. And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in proceſs of time, the <hi>independent party</hi> (or the great men of the Armie) ſerved the <hi>Presbyter</hi> or the <hi>Parliament</hi> the ſame trick. and therfore (Sir) had I nothing of God in me, <hi>but only a graine or two of reaſon left me,</hi> I should never ſide with anie partie in the World, in endeavouring the overturning the men that rule in England, unles it were a partie <hi>that in boones and priviledges did in reference</hi> to the People <hi>outbid all parties</hi> that ever went before them in Juſt and rationall things and ſoe to ty their hands, that if they would, they should not without the appare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t running the hazard of there owne ruine doe any miſcheef a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d therfore it is that by all the honeſt and <hi>induſtrious meanes</hi> that a <hi>laborious</hi> or <hi>ſtudious</hi> man can invent or take, will I by the <hi>asſiſtance of God</hi> preſerve my Intereſt in their owne <hi>bowells,</hi> amongſt thoſe honeſt and gallant men that live amongſt them, which have held forth that in worth and exellency, <hi>that in it ſelfe is good and profitable for all ſorts of reaſonable men that are not ſotts
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99537:8"/>and brute beaſts in their underſtandings,</hi> that never any held out before them, videlicet: THE AGREEMENT OF the people DATED MAY THE 1. 1649. And this Intereſt, I shall Increaſe, widen, and ſtrenghten as much as posſible I can with all perſons what ſoever that will embrace it, <hi>not doubting but that in the concluſion it will prove like Aarons rod that devoured the rods of all the Egiptian conjurers</hi> Exodus the 7 and the 20 <hi>„Swallowing up all Intereſts into it ſelfe.„</hi> And you may remember when I was indited for my life at <hi>Guildhall</hi> October 1649, that it was laid unto my <hi>charge</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Inditement</hi> as an act of <hi>treaſon that I had held out in print the ſame thing to the Prince</hi> by name: the words of which as they were conteined in the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement,</hi> yow may read, in <hi>the firſt part of the hiſtorie of my ſaid tryall</hi> page 58, 59, 60. And I muſt now acknowledge unto yow, that a learned, (and I am ſure of it as honeſt a) judge as ever I knew in England, videlicet: BARON RIGBY upon a ſerious diſcourſe with him: told me, in theſe verſe words, <q>that if God should ſuffer the Prince to follow the advice conteined in the three foreſaid pages; that in one three or 4 moneths after, he would not give SIXE PEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CE for all the Parliaments Intereſt in England.</q> And leaſt I should faile of my purpoſe, in maintaineing the <hi>peace of mine owne Conſcience,</hi> and my Intereſt among my foreſaid <hi>honeſt Freinds</hi> in England, I have for many yeares together and ſtill doe give unto my ſelfe this mot to, <hi>„that honeſty is the beſt Policy„</hi> as being the <hi>trueſt,</hi> moſt <hi>laſting</hi> and <hi>ſucceſsfull</hi> ïn the world, all things being truly and duly weighed, and confidered from firſt to laſt. In the maintaining of which I have for many yeares <hi>walked,</hi> and doe reſolve by the asſiſtance of God allmighty, <hi>ſo to doe to my dieing day,</hi> all though all the <hi>ſorrowes</hi> of the world should be my portion therfore.</p>
            <p>And therfore it is, that I have fixed my reſolution <hi>„to be irrevocably„</hi> one of thoſe, that doe and shall hold forth ſuch a thing to the people of England, <hi>as is truly able to take of all their jealouſies and feares from them,</hi> that if I should get up with my Intereſt, I intend by my ſelfe or by my Intereſt, to doe that with them, which the <hi>forementioned perſons</hi> did when they had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined their ends to get uppermoſt, <q>which was to ride the people and abuſe them rather wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe then thoſe that were before them, whom they had pulld downe:</q> and walke in larger way ies of wickednes then their predeceſſors, as may be clearly ſeen in ABSALOM and JEHU. for which, <hi>God cut them short as is verified</hi> by 2 Sam: 15, 10, 11, 12, 14, 23. and Chap. 16, 20, 21. and Chap. 17. 1, 2, 18, 23, 26. and 2 Kings 10, 29, 30, 31, 32. and <hi>„who ever shall read but the Parliaments firſt Remonſtrance„</hi> dated December 1641 „printed in the firſt part of the booke of their declarations„ page 3, 4, 5, &amp;c. „and their declaration of the 19 of May 1642 page 207, 214. and their declaration of the 26 of May 1642 page 263, 264, 267, 270. and their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Auguſt 1642 page 491, 492, 494, 496 and their Reply to the Kings anſwer of theirs of the 26 of May 1642 page 693. and read alſo their ſaid booke page 36, 342, 656, 660, 690, and their declarations of the 6 of May 1643 and of the 17 of April 1646 in the 2 de part of the booke of their declarations„ fol: 95, 879, and you shall clearly find they held forth moſt <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious expresſions</hi> to the People; of regaining their <hi>„loſt Lawes liberties and freedomes„</hi> as that which was not only their principal aime, but alſo as that which was their <hi>obliged duty,</hi> and (ſay they) <hi>„woe be to us„ if we diſcharge not our duty.</hi> in order to which, <q>they adjure and call out upon all thoſe that have any ſenſe of piety, honour or compasſion to come in and helpe a diſtreſſed ſtate.</q> But they walkeing in too nigh an affinity <hi>„to Abſaloms</hi> and <hi>Iehues„ lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſteps,</hi> the Army layes ſeige unto them, and tells them ſoundly and particularly of it: and holds forth in effect the ſame things which they had done before them, but with a great deale of more <hi>luſtre and glorie</hi> then they had done. As appeares, by the <hi>Booke of the Armies declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions page</hi> 23, 25, 26, 35, 37, 39, 42, 43, 44.</p>
            <p>Which pages being red with ſeriouſnes, will make it clearly appeare, <q>that their words were ſmoother then oile, nay dropped like the hony combe, into the mouths of the hungry oppreſſed People. How were their words ſeemingly bedewed with teares of pitty and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pasſion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99537:8"/>to the diſtreſſed people? how did they repreſent their hearts divided and rent in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with heareing the doleful cryes and beholding the bloodie teares of the oppreſſed? what profeſſed gallant reſolutions did the ſeeming deepe impresſions that the peoples miſeries had made upon their hearts, beget in them? how did they appearingly ſlight their eſtates and the injoyment of their neareſt relations? yea and of their <hi>deareſt blood</hi> in compariſon of the <hi>Peoples liberties?</hi> what gallant principles of freedome and righteouſnes, did they then profeſs? how lowd were their cries againſt all arbitrary powers whatſoever, <hi>and all ſeekers of private and particular Intereſts?</hi> how poſitive and abſolute were they in their reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, to have all the Liberties of the Nation cleared and ſecured? how did they ſeeme impatient of any delaies or protraction of time?</q>
            </p>
            <p>What <q>
                  <hi>Valiant Champions</hi> did theſe men appeare to bee for Englands Freedome? how did <hi>old English valour and undaunted</hi> courage to oppoſe the <hi>stouteſt enemies</hi> of the <hi>Public In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> and advantage, ſparkle forth in them upon June 4, 5, 1647. <hi>When they boldly enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in oppoſition to the Parliament and their ſpecial orders, not to disband nor to divide, nor ſuffer themſelves to be disbanded or divided, untill they had ſecurity that the free borne people of England should not be ſubject to the like injury, oppresſion and abuſe as had bin lately attempted to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed upon them?</hi> Did ever the moſt faithfull patriots to the moſt noble Nation of England paſs a larger engagement to their Countrie then this? who could have forborne to conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, that theſe would have bin our worthy Ehuds</q> (of whoſe valour and bravery for his Country you may read in Judges the 3.12, 13, 14, &amp;c.) <q>that would have peirced the bowells of every oppreſſour and deſtroyer of England? who could upon the ſight of this engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but imagin, that theſe would never have given themſelves reſt, untill they had ſeen the <hi>top-ſtone laid in the beautyous Fabric of Englands native Freedome?</hi> did they not oblige them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this ingagement, to bid defiance to every oppreſſor and abuſer of the People in <hi>Parliament, Committees, amongſt Iudges or Lawyers</hi> and all others whatſoever? were they not hereby bound to ſtand like the Jewes with <hi>good Nehemiah,</hi> with their ſwords in their hands, <hi>not only untill Englands breaches were repaired, but alſo untill the ſtrongeſt posſible iron gates were compoſed and ſet up to defend the</hi> Conſcientious Perſons, Liberties and Eſtates of all English men from oppreſſors? indeed could any engage to procure more perfect Freedome for the People, then they did in this engagement? can more be ſaid then this, <hi>that they would have ſecurity, that the People should not be ſubjest to the like injuries or abuſes, as had bin at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted?</hi> All men know there had bin attempts to offer all kinds and degrees of wrong and abuſe to the people, and therfore they promiſed and engaged to ſecure them for the future from them all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly; how were the pureſt, and moſt exact principles of Freedome and of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, profeſſed by theſe, to be <hi>the only grounds upon which they thus engaged, even againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament?</hi> The undefiled Law of Nature, was declared to be the rule of their proceedings. <hi>In their Declaration of June</hi> 14, 1647. the eſtablishment of common and equall right and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the whole Nation, <hi>was promiſed should be their Study,</hi> all purpoſes and deſignes to advance any private Intereſt, <hi>were moſt ſolemnly diſ-avowed and diſclaimed.</hi> Yea when the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament unvoted and expunged at their deſire from their journal Booke, thoſe votes wherby the Soldiers were declared enemies for petitioning in order to their ſatisfaction; <q>yet theſe men profeſſed ſuch principles of Freedome and common good, <hi>that they ſlighted that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular reparation given them, in that great caſe of common concernement</hi>
               </q> And in their Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance of the 23 of June 1647 declared, <q>that they did not value or regard their owne inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries or reparations in compariſon to the conſequence of the one or prejudice of the other</q> videlicet, „the future ſecurity of common right and Freedome in the Nation.</p>
            <p>Nay; how did theſe pretended heroic patriots ſeeme to diſdeigne ſelfish private Intereſts
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99537:9"/>or advantages? <q>
                  <hi>they ſeemed to thinke it too baſe, ſordid and unworthy for their pure Spirits</hi> to be a mercenary Armie, to ſerve the Arbitrary power of a ſtate for money or gold, and therfore they diſavowed their ſtanding as ſuch an Armie and declared; that they tooke up Armes in judgement and conſcience, as called forth by the Parliaments Declarations to the defence of their owne and the Peoples rights Freedomes and Liberties?</q> and were not their avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Principles as purely free, as thus truly public? for they declared, <q>the equitable ſenſe of the Law to be ſupreme to the Letter, and to diſpenſe with it, when the Safety of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is concerned. And likewiſe. <hi>That all authority is fundamentally ſeated in the Office</hi> and but miniſterially in the perſons.</q> Were ever clearer principle, of Freedome planted in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>heroic hearts</hi> then proceded from theſe mens mouthes; and <q>
                  <hi>they penned even by Ireton himſelfe the preſent Generall his ſonn in Law, and apeece of his heart and ſoule? die not every</hi>
               </q> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerning eye, ſee the tendency of theſe gallant pure principles to be <hi>perfect Freedome and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon juſtice?</hi> Were not the hearts of the oppreſſed people by the ſight of theſe declared princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and ingagements upon them, <q>Filled with liveing hopes of perfect Freedome from all Kinds of tyrannie and oppresſion, though sheltred under never ſo viſible and ſpecious formes of Parliamentary power, &amp;c.? did not every unprejudiced and truly English heart, expect that the <hi>crooked wills</hi> of men should no more have bin the meaſure of Englands Freedome, But only the ſtreighteſt rule of Nature?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly; what fiery zeale and burning Indignation, did theſe our <hi>ſeeming ſaviours</hi> breath forth againſt thoſe they judged the invaders of our native Freedomes and obſtructers of their ſpeedy ſettlement? <q>Were not their words ſpeares and ſwords and hot burning coales, againſt Sir Philip Stapleton and the reſt of that faction?</q> Did not theſe our hopefull and ſeeming Patriots, <q>teach the tongues of the whole Soldiery to cry aloud at New-market and Triploe heaths <hi>juſtice, juſtice, juſtice! againſt thoſe invaders of Englands Freedomes?</hi>
               </q> Was it not the firſt borne of their deſires? yea were they not ſo tranſported with zeale for the removall of thoſe membres whom they called apoſtates; that in their ſaid remonſtrance of June 23, 1646 dated at St. Albans, <q>they pręfixed a certaine day to the Parliament for their ſuſpenſion from the houſe, menaceing and threatning them to take an extraordinary way, unleſs that by the preęfixed day they were ſuſpended?</q> And appearingly ſo ſollicitous were they of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geing the houſe from all obſtructers of juſtice, common good and Freedome; that when the Parliaments commisſioners on July the 7, 1647 incited them to haſten the treaty betweene the Armie and Parliament for a ſettlement; they anſwered <q>that no comfortable effect of a trealy could be expected, ſo long as the Parliament was conſtituted of ſome perſons, whoſe Intereſts were contrary to common good booke of their Declarations page 78</q> thus they preſented themſelven even <hi>jealous</hi> for the peoples ſake, and induſtrious even to <hi>emulation</hi> for <hi>„freedome and juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly; how tedious irkeſome to theſe our <hi>ſeeming deliverers</hi> were the delaies in clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and ſecureing the peoples liberties, <hi>when the hopes of the People deferred made their very hearts ſick:</hi> page 77? How did they profeſs the neareſt and deareſt ſympathy with the peoples oppresſions in their ſaid Declaration of June 14? And did they not upon July 23 declare, <q>that their reſpect to the peoples ſafety inforced them to admit of no longer delayes, and that they could allow the houſe not above four or 5 daies wherein they might give aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and ſecurity to them and to the People of a ſafe and ſpeedy proceeding to ſettle the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and Nations Rights and Freedomes?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>ſpeedy</hi> ſettleing of common right and Freedome was viſibly and declaredly the choyceſt object of all their actions and intentions, that was ſeemingly the golden ball of all their contention,. „the fruit that their ſoules ſo exceedingly ſeemed to luſt„ after, and the ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate pretended end of all their painfull and hazardous race? <q>Whatſoever they deſired
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99537:9"/>for themſelves, was profeſſed to be inſiſted upon onely, in relation to the public ends aſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſaid.</q> Did not their Hearts ſeeme ſo far inflam'd with deſire of the ſettlement of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples right and Freedomes, <q>that no quiet, reſt, content, or ſatisfaction of mind could pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs them ſo long as the People groaned under tyranie and oppresſion?</q> yea they ſeemed ſo far to preferr the peoples good before their owne advantage, <q>that they declared they would never have entred into ſo hot a conteſt with the Parliament for reparations for their private wrongs and abuſes ſuffered from them, or their incroachments upon their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Freedomes, <hi>had not their ſuffering thoſe particular wrongs, bin prejudicial to common and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal right and Freedome.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sir; Behold theſe your great commanders and <hi>ſeemingly Religious</hi> Freinds thus cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with the glorious garment of their owne Declarations, of ſuch a <hi>curious texture;</hi> thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with variety of the faireſt promiſes as ſo many „bright oriental pearles„ and doe they not appeare like <hi>„Abſolom, without ſpot or blemith from head to foote„</hi> 2 Samuel 14, 25, „are they not like to <hi>Saul higher by the head then all the people</hi> 1 Sam: 9, 2. „can you forbeare to cry, there is none in the world like unto them?„ Did ever more hopefull ſonns ſpring from Englands fruitfull wombe? Did ever more lightſome ſtarrs ariſe in this Horizon? <q>Did not their hearts ſeeme to be the thrones of righteouſnes, and their breſts the habitation of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and compasſion to the oppreſſed and afflicted? was not juſtice as a robe to them, and mercy as a diademe? did they not appeare</q> to goe forth in the ſtrength of the Lord, To breake the Jawes of the wicked and oppreſſors, to pluck the ſpoile out of their teeth? Did they not then give ſuch hopes of deliverance to thoſe who were bound in chaines of tyrranie, and of releife to the poore afflicted, who had none to helpe them, <q>that the cares that heard their words rejoyced? and the blesſing of many which were ready to perish, came upon them?</q>
            </p>
            <p>And what Egle-eye could at firſt diſcerne, „that this glorious cloathing, <hi>was but painted paper?</hi>„ what jealous heart could have imagined, „that theſe promiſeing Patriots, <hi>were only ſweet mouthed diſſemblers?</hi>„ Who could have harboured the leaſts ſuſpition that theſe ſeeming viſible ſtarrs of heaven, <hi>„were but blazing Comets?„</hi> that would quickly <hi>turne their backs</hi> as they have perfectly done upon all theſe glorious promiſes and declarations, and prove the <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt apoſtates</hi> that ever the earth bore? and have made it their worke, <hi>„to impriſon, arreigne, condemne, shoot and murder men that have but put them in mind of their owne ſerious promiſes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, in which the preſent General himſelfe hath bin the cheif ringleader.</hi> And I wish that you and many of thoſe that „outwardly profeſs godlynes and honeſty in England„ were free from a zealous countenanceing of him in it. Although both they and hee cannot out know, that the righteous god of Heaven and earth, <q>brought a deſperate famine upon Iſrael for <hi>three yeares</hi> together, becauſe Saul had broke and violated that ſolemne contract, and engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Iſraelites had made with the <hi>heathen Gibeonites</hi>
               </q> although it was not volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, but obteined by fraud and deceit. Yet nothing would appeaſe the wrath of God, and ſatisfie the <q>
                  <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> but the hanging up of ſeven of the ſonns of Saul before the Lord, who was the man that had broken and violated the contract with them.</q> At the doeing of which, „the anger of God was turned away from Iſrael.„ All which appeares by Joshua 9, 3, 4, 5, 16, 17. and 2 Sam: 21:1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 14. And though it were that god proſpered IEHV while he was doeing his worke in cutting of the „wicked houſe of <hi>Ahabs</hi>„ &amp; made him proſperous and victorious in all his encountres, wherby his heart was ſo elevated and lifted up that he cried out <hi>Come ſee my zeale for the Lord,</hi> yet when he turned his back upon God and the waies of Juſtice and righteouſnes, „god then cut him and Iſrael short, and gave them up with a mighty ſlaughter to their Enemies„ the 2 Kings. Chap. 10. Therfore as a man that intirely loves my native Countrey I shall requeſt you to commend unto the ſerious and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99537:10"/>hearty conſideration of the LORD GENERALL and his Confederates the Advice of their valiant and learned Champion MR. MILTON, who haveing much spent his eloquence to rout the forces of SALMASIVS, in the Epilogue of his Latin booke, <hi>„called a Defenſe of the People of England„</hi> turnes his ſpeech to his Maſters that had ſet him on worke, whom he with much <hi>faithfullnes</hi> and Freedome beſpeakes on this manner. <q>One thing is remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neing and that haply of the greateſt moment, that you o my Countrymen and Fellow-Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyzens should your owne ſelves undertake the refutation of this your adverſary; which I doe not ſee how you can otherwiſe posſibly effect, ſave by endeavouring with tooth and naile to make your gallant actings the eternall confutation of all your Enemies raileings. God did graciouſly give care to your Vowes and moſt ardent petitions, when being oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with more then a <hi>single bondage</hi>
               </q> you fled to him for <hi>ſuccour.</hi> You in the firſt place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all Nations has he gloriously delivered from Tyranny and Superſtition, the greateſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, donbtles, of humane life, and moſt prejudiciall to all virtue and true Gallantry. <q>Into you it is that he hath inſuſed that height of courage, as that you have not doubted to be the firſt of Mankind, <hi>that have by a famous jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement tryed a King and punnished him being condemned,</hi> after that you had by your Armes procur'd his Conqueſt and ſurrender. After which ſo glorious a tranſaction, you ought</q> not now to thinke, much leſs to act any thing that is Mean and Low. <q>Which that it may be your commendation, you have no more to doe, but to take this courſe; namely, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke it appeare to all the World, that you are as well able in the middeſt of peace and diſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, moſt valiantly to conquer <hi>Ambition, Avarice, Mammon</hi> and thoſe corruptions of manners that attend proſperity; wich are wont to conquer other Nations and generations of men; as you have bin to vaquish your Enemies in a time of Warr; and to shew forth as much <hi>Iuſtice, Temperance</hi> and <hi>Moderation</hi> in the preſervation of your Liberties, as ever you have manifeſted courage in caſting the <hi>yoake of bondage</hi> from of your necks.</q> By theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and theſe alone, <q>by ſuch teſtimonies as theſe alone, you will be able to evince, that you are none of thoſe <hi>public Enemies, Traitors, Theives, Murderers, Parricides, Fantaſtic Enthuſiaſts</hi> whom this man railes upon; that you have not, moved with <hi>ambition or a desire to invade anothers right,</hi> nor pricked and ſpurred on with <hi>ſedition,</hi> any baſe luſts, madnes or ſury, <hi>murdered a King:</hi> but that you have, being <hi>inflamed</hi> with the love of <hi>liberty, religion, juſtice, common honeſty</hi> and your <hi>native Countrey,</hi> punished a tyrant. But if (which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee o good God may never come to paſs) your minds shall be otherwiſe enclined, if haveing bin valiant in warr, you shall in time of peace prove baſe and unworthy; you who have had manifeſt experience of <hi>Gods fighting</hi> in ſuch a manner for you and againſt your enemies; if <hi>casting</hi> behind your backs ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are and never to be for gotten an example of divine Preſence</q> you shall forget to ſeare God and execute Righteouſnes; <q>for my part I shall certainly grant and conſeſs, (for it will be paſt all denial,] that all thoſe things are true which malignant liers and railers have at any time moſt ignonimiously thought or ſaid of you;</q> and that you shall in a short time find God more incenſed with wrath againſt you, then ever yet your enemies have found him averſe or you have felt him benigne, favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable „and fatherly-affected unto you, more then to all the Nations at this time inhabiting the face of the whole earth and ſoe far for Mr. <hi>Miltons</hi> excellent and faithfull advice to them. And therefor now to goe on.</p>
            <p>Is it not true Sir, that <hi>ſucceſsive or new Parliaments equally choſen by the People</hi> of England are confeſſed on all hands, <hi>to be the very ſoul and life of all their Freedomes?</hi> and doe not the Law-bookes of England shew, <hi>that a Parliament</hi> (which in its owne conſtitution is excellent good phyſick but never was intended nor ever ſafely can be uſed for conſtant diet, becauſe it has allwaies bin pretended by the members thereof to be unlimited and arbitrary) <q>was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99537:10"/>and held fresh and fresh ſome times twice a yeare and that even before the Conqueſt</q> as is declared by <hi>Lambert</hi> in his collection of Lawes before the conqueſt, amongſt the Lawes of <hi>King Edgar</hi> chapter the 5, and by <hi>Sir Edward Cooke</hi> in his margent in the 9 page of his 4 part of Inſtitutes, in the Chapter of High-Court of Parliament which with other of the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of England, being by force of armes <hi>ſubdued by the Norman Conqueror,</hi> although the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of England forced him three ſeverall times to take his oath, after his being owned for King, <hi>to maintaine the English peoples Lawes and liberties,</hi> as being not able nor judgeing his conqueſt ſo good, juſt and ſecure a plea, to hold his new-gat crowne by, „as an after mutuall compact or Agreement with the People, or their repreſentatives„ over whom he was to rule. And therfore, as the <hi>Lord Cooke,</hi> in the foreſaid Chapter page the 12 declares „a Parliament or a kind of one was held even in the Conquerors time.„ See alſo to this purpooſe, the <hi>Lawbooke</hi> of the 21 of Edward the 3 ſolio the 60 and „the firſt part of the Lord Cookes Inſtitutes„ lib: 2. Chap. 10. Section 164. fol: 110. a. and came to be more Frequently uſed in his Succeſſors ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, „yea even to be once in two yeares in Edward the 1 or 2 his time„. at which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the people then <hi>grumbled</hi> as being an abſolute abridgement of their ancient and undoubted libertie, ‚to meet more frequently in their nationall and public aſſemblies„ to treat and conclude of things for their weale &amp; better being. The want of which in ancient time, ‚loſt the Island of Brittanie to the Romans„ as the ſaid <hi>Lord Cooke</hi> declares in the ſaid 4 part of his Inſtitutes folio 9, out of <hi>Tacitus</hi> in the life of <hi>Agricola</hi> page 306. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reupon it was enacted in full Parliament in Edward the third his time, <hi>that the King</hi> (who was the Peoples Officer of truſt) „should aſſemble &amp; call the People together in Parliament once every yeare or oftner if need required;„ as appeares by the ſtatute of the 4 of Edward the 3 Chapter the 14. But becauſe this was not conſtantly uſed by that King, but that ſometimes he made <hi>intervalls</hi> of three or ſower yeares betwixt <hi>Parliament</hi> &amp; <hi>Parliament,</hi> which was ſtill a diminution of the <hi>very Soule and Life of all the Peoples liberties</hi> vide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icet <hi>Frequent</hi> &amp; <hi>Often new Parliaments:</hi> therfore in the 36 yeare of his raigne, annuall Parliaments are provided. In theſe very words; <hi>Item for maintenance of the ſaid articles &amp; ſtatutes and redreſs of divers mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcheifs &amp; greivances whieh daily happen, a Parliament shall be holden every yeare; as another time was ordained</hi> by a ſtatute of the fourth of Edward the third Chapter the 14. and though in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ages it hath many times bin otherwiſe practiſed, yet the ſtatutes being ſtill in force, the parliaments anſwer to the King in the booke of Declarations, pag: 709 holds good, <hi>that the practiſe is noe argument againſt the right.</hi> But the late <hi>King Charles</hi> exceedingly faileing to put theſe Lawes in execution, in the <hi>Frequent calling of Parliaments;</hi> &amp; alſo when he had called them <hi>diſſolved</hi> them at his pleaſure &amp; ſo made them uſeles to the Nation; <hi>Both which the Parliament moſt notably declared was againſt his truſt, in their Declaration of November the</hi> 2, 1642. firſt part of the booke of their Declarations, page 70, &amp; 702, 709, &amp;c. <hi>of which the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament moſt bitterly complained in their firſt Remonſtrance</hi> Booke of Declarations Part 1 page 5, 6, 11 &amp; in page 10, 11, ibidem, they poſitively declare, <q>that his deſtroying of thoſe two grand Freedomes of the People videlicet, frequent, new, &amp; ſucceſſive Parliaments &amp; free debates therein; <hi>had corrupted and diſtempered the whole frame &amp; government of the Nation &amp; brought in nothing but deſtruction &amp; waies of tyranny.</hi>
               </q> For the preventing of which for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the Parliament got an Act to paſs in the 16 yeare of the late King, which was the firſt yeare of this <hi>long-lived Parliament,</hi> to confirme every tittle of the two fore mentioned acts for annuall Parliaments; &amp; further, in that act they ſay thus, <hi>that whereas it is by experience found, that the not holding of Parliaments according to the two forementioned acts, hath produced ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry &amp; great miſcheifes &amp; inconveniencyes to the Kings Majesty, the Church &amp; comment weale, for the prevention of the like miſcheifs &amp; inconveniencyes for the time to come;</hi> be it enacted by the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty with the conſent of the Lords Spirituall and temporall and the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99537:11"/>Commons in this preſent. Parliament aſſembled, <hi>that the ſaid [laſt Forementioned) Lawes &amp; ſtatutes be from henceforth duly keps and obſerved.</hi> And moſt excellent &amp; worthy to be written in Letters of gold, were and are thoſe arguments that the <hi>Lord George Digby</hi> (though ſince a Cavalier) uſed in his public ſpeech in the houſe of Commons January 19, 1640 at and for the paſſing of the laſt forementioned Law; which ſpeech of his is recorded in a printed booke cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>ſpeeches &amp; paſsages of Parliament,</hi> page 12, 13 &amp; to page 21.</p>
            <p>And hath not the PRESENT GENERALL in his verball expreſſions confirmed all the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe things as moſt righteous and juſt? for, was it not hee or his ſonn in law IRETON (lately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed) that drew that <hi>excellent declaration</hi> of the Army dated <hi>Iune</hi> the 14, 1647 printed and published in the <hi>booke of their Declarations</hi> page 41, 42, 43 where they poſitively declare, <q>that they were ſo farr from deſigneing, or complying to have an arbitary power fixed or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for continuance in any perſons whatſoever, as that (ſay they) if we might be ſure to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine it, <hi>we cannot wish to have it ſo in the perſons of any whom we could moſt confide in,</hi> or who should appeare moſt of our owne opinions and principles, or whom we might have moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal aſſurance of or Intereſt in. but we doe &amp; shall much rather wish that the authority of this Nation in Parliaments</q> (rightly conſtituted, that is, <hi>„freely, equally &amp; ſucceſſively choſen„</hi> according to their originall intention) <q>may ever ſtand &amp; have its courſe &amp; therfore we shall applie our ſelves cheifly to ſuch things, as (by haveing Parliaments ſettled in ſuch a right conſtitution) may give moſt hopes of juſtice &amp; righteouſnes to flow downe <hi>equally to all,</hi> in that its ancient channel, without any overtures, tending either to overthrow, that founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of order &amp; government in this Kingdome, or</q> to engroſs that power for perpetuity into the hands of any particular perſons, or partie whatſoever. <q>And for that purpoſe, though (as we have found it doubted by many men, minding ſincerely the public good, but not wei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghing ſo ſully all conſequences of things) it may and is not unlike to prove, that, upon the ending of this Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; the election of a new, the Conſtitution of ſucceeding Parliaments as to the perſons elected may prove for the worſe many waies; yet, ſince neither in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purgeing of this Parliament, nor in the Election of new, we cannot promiſe to our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, or the Kingdome,</q> an aſſurance of juſtice, or other poſitive good from the hands of men, but thoſe who for the preſent appeare moſt righteous &amp; moſt for common good <hi>(„haveing an unlimited power fixed in them for life or pleaſure„)</hi> in time, may become corrupt, or ſettle into par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or factions; „or, on the other ſide, in caſe of new Elections, thoſe that should ſo ſucceed, may prove as bad or worſe then the former.„ We therfore humbly conceive that <hi>(„of two in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencyes the leſs being to be choſen„)</hi> the maine thing to be intended in this caſe <hi>(„and beyond which humane providence cannot reach, as to any aſsurance of poſitive good„)</hi> ſeemes to be this, viz. To provide, <q>that how ever unjuſt or corrupt the perſons of Parliament-men, in preſent or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may prove; or what ever ill they may doe to particular Parties (or to the whole in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular things) during their reſpective termes, or periods</q> yet they shall not have the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or advantage of an unlimited power fixed in them during their owne pleaſures, <q>wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to perpetuate injuſtice and oppreſſion upon any <hi>(without end or remedie)</hi> or to advance and uphold <hi>any one particular partie,</hi> faction, or intereſt whatſoever, to the oppreſſion or prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the community, &amp; the <hi>enſlaveing</hi> of the Kingdome to all poſterity; but that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may have an <hi>equall hope</hi> or poſſibility, if they have</q> made an ill choyce at one time, to mend it in another: <q>and the members of the Houſe themſelves <hi>may be in a capacity, to taſt of ſubjection as well as rule,</hi> &amp; may ſo be enclined to conſider of other mens caſes, as what may come to be their owne. And ſpeakeing a little</q> after of the Parliament whoſe power they ſay is ſo arbitrary &amp; in a manner unlimitted; in which regard, <hi>„it is moſt unfitt &amp; dangerous„</hi> (as to the Peoples intereſt] <hi>„to be fixed in the perſons of the ſame men dureing life or their owne pleaſures;„</hi> they add, that „Neither by the Originall conſtitution of this ſtate, was it, or ought it to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99537:11"/>ſo, <hi>nor does</hi>„ it (where ever it is &amp; continues ſo) <q>
                  <hi>render that ſtate any better then a meere Tyrannie, or the People ſubject to it, any biter then Vaſſals:</hi> But in all ſtates where there is any face of common Freedome,</q> and particularly in this ſtate of England (as is evident, both by many poſitive Lawes, &amp; ancient conſtant cuſtome) <q>the people have a right to new and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive elections unto that great and ſupreme truſt, at certaine periods of time, <hi>which is ſo eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall &amp; fundamentall to their Freedome,</hi> as it cannot, or ought not to be denied them, or with-held from them, and without which the houſe of Commons, is of very little concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the intereſt of the Commons of England. And therfore a little</q> below they po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively defire, <hi>that ſome determinate period of time</hi> may be ſet for the continuance of this and future Parliaments, <q>beyond which none shall continue and upon which the writts may of courſe yſſue out and new Elections ſucceſſively take place accordingly. And thus (ſay they) a firme foundation being laid in the Authority and conſtitution of Parliaments for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, at leaſt, of common and equal right and Freedome to our ſelves and all the Free-borne people of this Land, <hi>we shall for our parts freely and cheerfully committ our ſtock or share of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in this Kingdome into this common bottome of Parliaments</hi>
               </q> and though it may (for our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars) goe ill with us in one Voiage, <hi>yes we shall thus hope</hi> (if right be with us) <hi>to fare better in another.</hi> And did not the preſent <hi>Generall</hi> in his propoſalls of the 1 of Auguſt 1647 pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished to the view of the whole Nation, <q>preſs that a certaine period may by act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be ſet for the ending of this preſent Parliament, and that ſuch period be <hi>within a yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re at moſt?</hi>
               </q> See the booke of the Armies Declarations page 112. And did not the preſent Generall in his Remonſtrance of the 8 of Auguſt 1647 declare, <q>that it was his erneſt indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and the indeavor of the Armie, to ſettle a ſound and laſting peace on good termes for the Intereſt of the Nation? but in ſtead of the hoped for fruit of their labours and hazards and of the Nations vaſt expence (in the diſpenceing of juſtice and righteouſnes and the ſettleing and upholding of common right and Freedome to the people of England) wee found (ſaith the Generall &amp;c.) immediatly the croſs workings of a ſtrong and prevalent partie in the parliament and Kingdome, who [walkeing under the maske of the Parliaments Freinds but being in truth men of corrupt and private ends and Intereſts, different from and deſtructive to the real and common Intereſt of the Kingdome) made uſe of their power to <hi>obſtruct</hi> &amp; <hi>pervert juſtice,</hi> to injure, oppreſs and crush the peaceable and well-affected peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Kingdome; <hi>to abridge and overthrow all juſt Freedome and liberty,</hi> and drive on deſignes to ſet up a <hi>partie and faction</hi> in the Parliament and Kingdome, and <hi>(by the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a PERPETV AL PARLIAMENT]</hi> to dominere over and <hi>enſlave</hi> the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to poſterity, and for that end to make ſuch a peace with the King (if any] as without any juſt proviſion, <hi>for the common and true Intereſt of the People</hi> and the ſecurity therof for future;</q> which [ſaith the Generall &amp;c.) <hi>we were called out to vindicate and defend and had ſo long fought for. thoſe being</hi> (ſaith he &amp;c.) <hi>thoſe juſt and public ends for which ſo much blood and treaſure hath bin ſpilt and ſpent in the late warrs.</hi> See the booke of the Armies Declarations page 129, 132, 134. Did not the Armie in their <hi>grand Remonſtrance,</hi> of 16 of November 1648 preſented by them to the Parliament by the hands of COLL. EWERS (once my Major] and other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and tendered by them to the conſideration of the whole Kingdome, ſay as much <hi>for the neceſsity and utility of conſtant, equall, and ſucceſsive Parliaments,</hi> as it is all moſt impoſſible for any men in the world with tongues or penns to ſay more. Reade their expreſſions in page 15, 45, 46, 52, 56, 66, 67, 69. and are not theſe part of their words, where ſpeaking to the Parliament, doe they not earneſtly deſire them; Firſt, <q>that they would ſet ſome reaſonable and certaine period to their owne power, by which time (ſay they) that great and ſupreme truſt repoſed in you shall be returned into the hands of the people for and from whom you received it, that ſo you may give them ſatisfaction and aſſurance, that what you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99537:12"/>for againſt the King (for which they have bin put to ſo much trouble, coſt and loſs of blood) <hi>hath bin only for their Liberties &amp; Common Intereſt &amp; not for your owne perſonall Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt or power.</hi> Secondly, that there may be a ſound ſettlement of the peace and future Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Kingdome upon grounds of common Right Freedome and Safety, to the effect here following.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>that from the end of this, there may be a certaine ſucceſſion of future Parliaments) AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NV ALL OR BIENNIALL with ſecure</hi> proviſion. 1 <hi>For the certainty of their meeting, ſitting and ending.</hi> 2 <hi>For the equall diſtribution of Elections thereunto, to render the Houſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons as neare as may be an equall repreſentative of the whole people electing.</hi> 3 <hi>For the certainty of the peoples meeting (according to ſuch diſtributions) to elect, and for their full Freedome in elections. Provided that none who have ingaged or shall ingage in warr againſt the right of Parliament and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of the Kingdome therein, or have adhered to the Enemies thereof, may be capable of electing or being elected (at leaſt during a competent number of yeares) nor any other, who shall oppoſe or not joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in agreement to this ſettlement.</hi> 4 <hi>That it be declared, that (as to the whole Intereſt of the people of England) ſuch repreſentatives have and shall have the</hi> SVPREME POWER <hi>&amp; truſt, as to the makeing of Lawes, Conſtitutions and Offices, for the ordering, preſervation, and government of the whole, and that in the</hi> NEGATIVE <hi>they may not render up or give or take away any of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations</hi> of common-right, liberty or ſafety conteined in this ſettlement &amp; agreement: AND THIS TO BE ESTABLISHED BY A GENERALL CONTRACT OR AGREEMENT OF THE PEOPLE, WHICH THEY THERE REQUIRE MAY HAVE THEIR SUBSCRIPTIONS THE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REUNTO, and that withall it may be <hi>provided, that none may be capable of any benefit by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement who shall not conſent &amp; ſubſcribe thereunto, nor any King be admitted to the Crowne, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon to any Office or place of public truſt without expreſs accord and ſubſcription to the ſame: and alſo they preſs the Parliament</hi> to conſider ſuch ſperial overtures as have bin tendred to them, in the petitions of well wishers to public good <q>and eſpecially and particularly <hi>That large petition from many in and about London dated the 11th of September</hi> 1648:</q> that ſo they may when they lay downe their truſt (which they preſs may be ſpeedily) leave a good favour behind them, both to the name of Parliaments &amp; alſo of men profeſſing Godlynes and therein cheifly to the honour of Allmighty God, who hath (in his rich grace and mercy) done ſuch wonders for them.</p>
            <p>And did not the <hi>preſent Generall</hi> &amp; the reſt of the Officers of the Armie draw up and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe to be preſented unto the Houſe upon the 20 of January 1649 or rather 1648 <hi>by Lieutenant Generall Hammond, Coll: Okey and</hi> other Officers of the Armie, a petition and a <hi>draught of ſuch an Agreement,</hi> which was afterwords by their order printed at London <q>
                  <hi>by Iohn Partrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, Rich: Harford, Giles Calvert &amp; George Whittington</hi>
               </q> all Bookeſellers in London? In which ſaid petition they uſe theſe very words. <q>Now as nothing did in our owne hearts mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re juſtifie our late undertakeings towards many members in this Parliament, <hi>then the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity therof in order to a ſound ſettlement in the Kingdome and the integritie of our intentions to make uſe of it only to that end;</hi> So we hold our ſelves obliged to give the people all aſſurance pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that our oppoſeing the corrupt cloſure endeavoured with the King, <hi>was not in deſigne to hinder peace or</hi> ſettlement, (therby to render our employments, as Soldiers, neceſſary to be continued) and that neither that extraordinary courſe we have taken, nor any other proceedings of ours, <hi>have bin intended for the ſetting up of any particular Party or Intereſt, by or with which to uphold our ſelves in power and dominion over the Nation,</hi> but that it was and is the deſire of our hearts in all we have done</q> (with the hindering of that imminent evill and deſtructive conjunction with the King) <q>
                  <hi>to make way for the ſettlement of a peace and government of the Kingdome, upon grounds of common Freedome and ſafety.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And the introduction of the ſaid <hi>agreement</hi> is in theſe very words; <q>
                  <hi>An agreement</hi> of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99537:12"/>people of England and the places therewith incorporated, for a ſecure &amp; preſent peace u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon grounds of common right Freedome and ſafety.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Haveing by our late labours and hazards made it appeare to the world, <hi>at how high a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te wee value our juſt Freedome,</hi> &amp; God haveing ſo far owned our cauſe, as to deliver the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies thereof into our hands; we doe now hold our ſelves bound in mutuall duty to each other, to take the beſt care we can for the future, TO AVOID BOTH THE DAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GER of returning into a ſlaveish condition &amp; the chargeable remedie OF ANOTHER WARR. For as it cannot be imagined, that ſo many of our Country men would have oppoſed us in this quarrel, if they had underſtood their owne good, ſo may we hopefully promiſe to our ſelves, that <hi>WHEN OVR COMMON RIGHTS AND LIBER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIES SHALL BE CLEARED,</hi> their endeavours will be diſappointed, that ſeeke to make them ſelves our Maſters. Since therefore our former oppreſſions, and not yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded troubles;</q> 
               <hi>have been occaſioned, either by want of frequent national meetings in councel, or by the undue or unequal conſtitution thereof, or by rendring thoſe meetings uneffectuall.</hi> We are fully <q>reſolved &amp; agreed (God willing) to provide, that hereafter our Repreſentatives be neither left to an uncertainty for time nor be unequally conſtituted, nor made uſeles to the ends for which they are intended</q> In order whereunto we declare &amp; agree;</p>
            <p n="1">(1) <hi>THAT, TO PREVENT THE MANY INCONVENIENCYES, AP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PARENTLY ARISEING FROM THE LONG CONTINV ANCE OF THE SAME PERSONS IN SVPREME AVTHORITY, this preſent Parliament end and diſolve upon or before the laſt day of April, in the yeare of our Lord</hi> 1649.</p>
            <p>And for the excellency <hi>common utility</hi> &amp; ſafety of ſettleing the diſtreſſed Nation of England upon ſuch an agreement, after the shakeing the foundations of the government therof, by ſo many bloody warrs, in their printed Declaration annexed to the ſaid agreement wherby they recommend it to the ſerious conſideration of the people of England, they have theſe verie words; <hi>Wee shall not otherwiſe commend it</hi> (that is the ſaid agreement) <hi>then to ſay it conteines,</hi> THE <hi>BEST AND MOST HOPEFVLL FOVNDATIONS FOR THE PEACE AND FVTVRE WELL GOVERNMENT OF THIS NATION, THAT WE CAN DEVISE OR THINKE ON WITHIN THE LINE OF HV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANE POWER, and ſuch wherein all the people intereſsed in this Land</hi> [that have not parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Intereſts of advantage &amp; power over others, divided from that which is common &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blic) <hi>are indifferently &amp; equally provided for, ſave where any have juſty forfeited their share in that common Intereſt by oppoſeing it, and ſo rendred themſelves incapable thereof (at leaſt) for ſome time. And we call the Conſciences of all that read or heare it to wittnes, whether we have therein provided or propounded any thing of advantage to our ſelves in any capacity above</hi> others, <hi>OR OVGHT, BVT WHAT IS AS GOOD FOR ONE AS FOR ANOTHER.</hi> And a little further in the ſaid Declaration, they aver and ſay.</p>
            <p>And we for our parts, <hi>being far from any deſire or thought to aſſume or exerciſe a law-giveing, or judicial power over the Kingdome, or to meddle in any thing ſave the fundamentall ſettleing of that power in the moſt EQV, ALL &amp; hopefull way for COMMON RIGHT, FREEDOME AND SAFETY</hi> (as in this Agreement) <hi>and haveing not meanes nor time for, nor the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity of ſome preſent generall ſettlement, admitting the delay of ſuch a conſideration, as ſeemes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite in relation to ſuch numerous particulars, we have purpoſely declined the inſerting of ſuch things into</hi> THIS AGREEMENT.</p>
            <p>And did not the preſent GENERALL &amp; the reſt of his Officers publish a Declaration dated in December 1648: which expreſſeth the reaſons of their then advance with their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to London, to purge (OR RATHER PLVCK VP BY THE ROOTES) the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? and doe they not in that Declaration poſitively declare, <hi>that the Parliaments treating
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99537:13"/>with the King and rejecting all better &amp; wholſomer counſells given them IS NO LESS THEN A TREACHEROVS OR CORRVPT NEGLECT OR AN APOST ATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZING FROM THE PVBLIC TRVST REPOSED IN THEM. Yet not AS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVMING to themſelves</hi> [as there in words they ſay] <hi>a ſtanding power of judgement (AS OF RIGHT OR TRVST) to conclude others thereby, acknowledging that to lie moſt properly in thoſe whom the people DVLY CHOOSE AND TRVST TO IVDGE FOR THEM. But conſidering that ſuch power, where ever it is, IS COMMITTED BVT IN TRVST, and that neither this Nation, nor any other people DID EVER GIVE VP THEIR NATV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RALL CAPACITIES OF COMMON SENSE OR REASON, as to the ends &amp; fundamentalls of that trust. And as for the Parliaments breach of truſt, there being no formal power of man in beeing to appeale to, in the preſent caſe,</hi> they poſitively declare, <hi>They cannot but exerciſe that common judgement which in their NATVRALL CAPACITY is left to them,</hi> and therfore conſidering that <hi>the Parliaments then BREACH OF TRVST, was ſo tranſcendently great, as that it was an hazard of totall deſtruction to that Intereſt, &amp; to thoſe people, for which eſpecially</hi> (they ſay) <hi>the truſt was repoſed. And ſeeing there is no orderly &amp; open way left for a juſt ſucceſſion of another formal and proper judicature to bee appealed unto in due time,</hi> therfore they there renounced the then Parliament, AS NO PARLIAMENT AT ALL, <hi>&amp; with confidence APPEALED TO THE COMMON IVDGEMENTS OF INDIF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FERENT AND VNCORRVPTED MEN, exciteing all thoſe that yet were faithfull to their truſt in the Parliament to COME OVT &amp; joyne with them, and in ſuch a caſe of extremity they promiſe to looke upon them</hi> [not as a Parliament, but) <hi>as perſons materially haveing the cheife truſt of the Kingdome remaining in them, THOVGH NOT A FORM ALL STAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DING POWER, to be continued in them or drawne into ordinary president; yet the beſt and moſt rightfull that can be had, as the preſent State and exigency of affaires then ſtood; and wee shall</hi> (ſay they) <hi>accordingly owne them, adhere to them &amp; be guided by them, in their FAITHFVLL PROSECVTION OF THEIR TRVST,</hi> which they there declare, <hi>to be onely in order unto</hi> (MARKE IT WELL) <hi>and</hi> VNTILL THE INTRODVCEING OF A MORE FVLL AND FORMALL POWER IN A JVST REPRESENTATIVE TO BE SPEEDILY INDEAVOVRED AND RATIFIED BY AN AGREEMENT AND SVBSCRIPTION OF THE PEOPLE THEREVNTO.</p>
            <p>And did not the preſent <hi>Generall</hi> (for upon him I principally looke, and judge him in a manner to be all in all, and not only one man but; his word in England, to be more then ten thouſand) <hi>lay it as an act of treaſon, to</hi> the late <hi>King Charles,</hi> charge his in his (for ſo I may truly call it) late impeachment of him, dated the 20 of January 1648: <hi>that he had KEPT</hi> OF FREQVENT AND SVCCESSIVE PARLIAMENTS OR NATIONAL MEETINGS IN COVNCEL, <hi>which</hi> (as before is averred) <hi>ought to be once every yeare or oftner if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire?</hi> And did not the <hi>Generalls</hi> then two principall agents, to wit, the LORD PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIDENT BRADSHAW and Mr. JOHN COOKE now Lord cheife juſtice in Ireland, notably with all their Eloquence and Rhetoric aggravate that againſt the King, as a moſt tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent crime? ſee the 11 page of the <hi>Lord Bradshawes last ſpeech againſt the King,</hi> being u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the 27 of January 1648, and <hi>Mr. Iohn Cooke</hi> his State of the Kings Caſe page 7, 11, 14, 17, 18, 20. in the laſt of which, Mr. JOHN COOKE averrs, THAT THE PEOPLE OF ENGLAND NOT ONLY BY SEVERAL STATVTE LAWES OVGHT TO HAVE A PARLIAMENT ONCE A YEARE OR OFTNER IF NEED REQVIRE, <hi>BVT ALLSO OF COMMON RIGHT THEY OVGHT TO HAVE IT; and that the Kings makeing of Parliaments when he called them, VSELES to the END for which they were inſtituted, was a crime in him EQVALL to his not calling them, for nine or ten yeares together.</hi> And I wish the preſent Generall, were not much more guiltie then ever the King
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99537:13"/>was, <hi>of all thoſe tamperings, juggleings &amp; machiavilian devices, that he ſpeakes of in his</hi> 17, 18 and 20 pages, <hi>to make a Parliament uſeles in any thing,</hi> BVT TO SERVE HIS OWNE LVSTS AND OPPRESS THE PEOPLE THEREBY. So that then by <hi>Mr. Iohn Coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes</hi> concluſion, to ſpeake in his owne words, <hi>the Generall may throw the gauntles &amp; challenge all the MACHIAVELS IN the world to invent ſuch an EXQVISITE PLATFOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ME of tyrannicall domination &amp; ſuch a PERFECT TYRANNIE without</hi> MAIME <hi>or</hi> BLEMMISH <hi>as he is Prince or Emperour of, and that by a Law, which ſaith</hi> Mr. JOHN COO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KE is worſt of all.</p>
            <p>And did not the preſent <hi>Generall</hi> before the late battel at Worceſter, ingage and promiſe before God &amp; ſeveral Officers of his Armie, &amp; of the good people of England; that if God bleſſed him with that victorie, he would <hi>immediately</hi> be the effectual inſtrument to <hi>procure unto the people of England their naturall common, legal and undoubted birth-right,</hi> TO ELECT AND CHOOSE A NEW PARLIAMENT? and did he not after the battaile, engage the ſame? and did he not come up to London and in the Parliament Houſe immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his comeing up <hi>expreſs himſelfe full of zeale for the immediate calling a new-Parliament, „As that which they were bound in Conſcience and duty both to God and Man forthwith to call„?</hi> And were not the Spirits and Hearts of thouſands and ten thouſands of the honeſt people of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land refreshed thereby, and cried him up as their <hi>earthly Saviour &amp; Redeemer</hi> therfore? yet was his carriage therein any other then A PERFECT CHEAT AND DECEIT, on purpoſe in peace &amp; quietnes to get <hi>disbanded</hi> &amp; ſcatterd all thoſe forces that in their hearts longed for it, and in their words expreſſed ſo much, and it may be he feared were at <hi>Worceſtor</hi> twice ſo many, as hee, &amp; all thoſe that durſt then joyne with him againſt it. which neceſſitated him to give them good woords, and faire promiſes; till he got all the „new-raiſed forces <hi>(who were full of Life for a new Parliament)</hi> disbanded„ &amp; all his owne Regiments that he was <hi>jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of</hi> diſperſt &amp; <hi>ſcattered</hi> into ſmall companies abroad in the Nation¿ and under the <hi>preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce</hi> of caſe of the Peoples <hi>taxes,</hi> ordered hee not his Officers to <hi>disband</hi> a certaine number our of their troopes &amp; companies of the <hi>most choyceſt men</hi> that he was afraid were <hi>Poſſeſſed</hi> with ſuch principles? and did he not to the ſaddening of the Vniverſality of honeſt mens hearts in England, when hee imagined he had done his worke to his hearts deſire, vote &amp; declare the Parliament should <hi>(after they had ſate almoſt twelve yeares)</hi> ſit three yeares lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger if they pleaſed, and at three yeares end they may ſit as long as they or hee lives, if he pleaſe. So that the people shall never have a <hi>New Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And upon this, <hi>did not you</hi> and divers other honeſt men, <hi>Leaders or Preachers</hi> to ſeverall of the moſt CONSCIENTIOVS CONGREGATIONS OF INDEPENDENTS AND ANABAPTISTS in and about the Cittie of London, repaire to him, and with grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe of heart freely and fully to his face <hi>lay open his wickednes</hi> in this very thing, as the moſt groſs hypocriſie and baſenes that could be acted by a man? againſt which, did you not tell him, you judged your ſelves bound in duty and conſcience before God &amp; the world to beare wittnes; &amp; againſt this his practiſe to endeavour <hi>as of duty and of right,</hi> to the hazard of your lives and all that in this world you could call yours, <hi>„immediately to procure a new Parliament?</hi> and when by your diſcourſes with him, he grew choleric &amp; hot, and would not well endure freely to be ſpoke to, did not ſome of the <hi>„cheifeſt Independents</hi> amongſt your companie„ tell him to his face, <q>that ſeeing he was ſo altered &amp; changed from what he uſed to be, that now he would not endure plainely to be told his owne, you would leave him in his decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned condition and goe home to your cloſets, and by prayer cry aloud to God againſt him?</q> and have not ſome of the cheifeſt of the ſame company <hi>(I meane Independents]</hi> ſince declared to ſome of their acquaintance, that they abſolutely found and <hi>judged the Generall</hi> (now by cleare experience) <hi>to be as falſe &amp; as juggleing a man as the worſt or higheſt of his adverſaries had
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99537:14"/>ever reported him to bee?</hi> and that his <hi>juggleing</hi> &amp; deceit would be quickly the apparent ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of the ruine of all the honeſt men in England? And did not <hi>you all lay</hi> your heads to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and abſtract the very <hi>quint-eſſence</hi> of your braines into reaſons deducted both from the <hi>Right, Profit</hi> and <hi>Necesſity of haveing a</hi> NEW PARLIAMENT out of hand, &amp; the duty that lies upon your Conſciences <hi>particularly,</hi> to ſtickle vigorouſly for the procureing of it? and did you not deliever <hi>the ſaid reaſons</hi> in writeing to the <hi>Generalls</hi> owne hands¿ and upon his continuing obſtinate againſt your juſt deſires, have you not ſince kept SEVERALL FASTS AT GREAT ALL-HALLOWES IN THAMES STREET LONDON, <hi>from morning till night, twelve</hi> 14, <hi>or</hi> 16, <hi>of you praying in one day?</hi> and have not your hearts bin lifted up to God, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to beg aſſiſtance from him, to inable you to goe on <hi>couragiously</hi> and actively with faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnes and ſucceſs, not withſtanding all oppoſition to the contrary to accomplish fully that <hi>great good</hi> for the people of England <hi>„to wit: the procureing a new-elected Parliamen for them?</hi> And hath not the <hi>Generall</hi> himſelfe with his <hi>Sycophantizeing</hi> agents &amp; Chaplaines MR. or Dr. OWEN <hi>the new Deane of Chriſt-church, Mr. LOCKYER, Mr. SYDRACH SIMP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SON, AND Mr. PHILIP NYE bin extremely curaged and mad with you therfore,</hi> and uſed to ſeverall of you not only <hi>threats,</hi> but alſo <hi>ſugred perſwaſions</hi> to cauſe you to deſiſt the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re from; &amp; have you not nevertheleſs perſevered and gone on; and ſent your Letters and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents to all (or the moſt part of] your Freinds, <hi>in all the Counties of England or Wales:</hi> to excite them to joyne with you therein? and can you now without <hi>horror of Conſcience</hi> upon any pretences whatſoever, and an apprehenſion of the <hi>Wrath, Vengeance,</hi> and <hi>curſe both of God and man to ſeaze immediatly upon you and your Families,</hi> goe back, ſit ſtill, <hi>or grow cold or lukewarme?</hi> eſpecially if you but ſeriously read, ponder and meditate upon, what I have here writt unto you, which is all the Inference that at preſent I shall draw from the premiſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Only I shall now take the Libertie, to give you the reaſons why I write theſe lines to you &amp; the</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt is, Becauſe I know no man of mine ancient acquaintance, that profeſſeth <hi>Religion, Zeale, Conſcience</hi> or <hi>Common-good,</hi> as your ſelfe doth, that is ſo familiarly acquainted with all the <hi>fower forementioned great Sword-men,</hi> or the major-part of them, as your ſelfe is: and ſo well heard by them as you are: and becauſe I hate to <hi>grapple</hi> in good earneſt with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt adverſary I have in the world, but I will (if it bee posſible,) tell him before hand <hi>what weapons I will bee at with him,</hi> that ſo he may if he pleaſe chooſe a Compoſure, if not let him doe his pleaſure, and I shall doe the beſt I can for my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe I underſtand ſince I ſaw you, you have bin very civil and reſpective, <hi>to my poore diſtreſsed &amp; diſconſolate wife.</hi> and leaſt by any after actions of mine you should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of any civilitie you have alreadie done her, or be unwilling to doe her any more hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; becauſe I would give as much ſatisfaction to her <hi>(whom my ſoule hath loved &amp; ſtill doth love)</hi> (if I know any thing of mine owne heart <hi>(as intirely as ever husband loved a wife)</hi> as far as with a good conſcience &amp; mine owne Saſetie I poſſibly can; and that I am a rationall man &amp; willing to ſtoope, for her Satisfaction, ſo Farr as with the maintaineing of mine owne peace it may bee.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Generall</hi> haveing medled with me, without the leaſt shadowe of ground or cauſe, or the leaſt provocation given him by me, I am confident of it; and thereby pickt a quarrell with me as <q>
                  <hi>Benhadad the King of Aſſyria did with the King of Iſrael,</hi> who would not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with any thing that the King of Iſrael could profer to him, unleſs he would give him every thing that was pleaſaunt in his eyes, as appeares the</q> 1 Kings 20 who paid deare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for his Inſolency <hi>as in that Chapter you may read.</hi> And I for my part, challenge the <hi>Generall</hi> to inſtance if he can, any one ſeemeing provocation that I have of late given him, for I am ſure of it, ſince our laſt outwardly ſolemne reconcilement, I never in the leaſt <hi>Diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> him, but waited upon him, ſince his comeing from <hi>Worceſter</hi> at his owne Houſe, <hi>and had
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99537:14"/>an houre or two's private diſcourſe with him in his Gallerie, &amp; gave him all the ingagements from me that are fit,</hi> either for a man of Honour, Conſcience, or Integritie to give to a great man, <hi>whoſe abſolute vaſſall he cannot bee.</hi> And he aſſured mee he would receive no Information a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me behind my back, but he would ſend for me and ſpeak with me, before it should ſtick or find beleife with him, proteſting he had <hi>abſolutely buried</hi> in the grave of forgetfullnes the remembrance of all by-paſt things betwixt us, and now should be as ready to ſerve me, as any Freind I had in England, <hi>commending my Ingenuitie and proffers to him in the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt SIR ARTHVR HASILRIG</hi> &amp; my Freinds, which was in the firſt place; I prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the <hi>Generall</hi> that ſo hee might ſee, [as I told him] that I had no deſire to ruffle with any that I knew hee was intimate with &amp; that I had a very high apprehenſion of his Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; of the Juſtice of the cauſe, which for my Freinds I mannaged againſt <hi>SIR AR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THVR HASILRIG</hi> and therfore Firſt, that if his Honour with deliberation would vouchſafe to heare the buyſines fully, I would engage if SIR ARTHVR would doe the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, THAT MY FREINDS SHOULD ENGAGE THEMSELVES IN A BOND OF 20 THOU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SAND POUND FINALLY TO STAND TO HIS JUDGEMENT AND THEREIN TO ACQUIESCE WITHOUT FURTHER STRUGGLEING. <hi>But he told me his occaſions were great</hi> &amp; many and would not permit him time fully to heare ſo large a buſynes, as he was afraid it was. Vnto which I replied My Lord;</p>
            <p>Then in the 2d place if your <hi>Lordship</hi> pleaſe to propound this unto <hi>Sir Arthur,</hi> that if he pleaſe to chooſe any <hi>two Officers</hi> in your Armie, of thoſe that hee leaves wee will chooſe two more.</p>
            <p>Or 3dly; if he like better to chooſe <hi>two Members of Parliament,</hi> wee will chooſe two mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re; and I will engage my Freinds shall bind themſelves in the foreſaid bonds, <hi>to ſtand to their final judgement, provided that wherein they cannot agree, that ſo we may have an end, your Lordship shall decide it.</hi> Vnto which he replied, it was ſo faire, as fairer could not be offered by any man in the world, and moſt ſolemnly engaged himſelfe unto me (to uſe his owne words) to ſpeake <hi>effectually to Arthur about it,</hi> and at that time tooke of me my <hi>printed Booke, againſt</hi> SIR ARTHVR <hi>and the „fower unjuſt commisſioners at Haberdashers Hall:</hi> And promiſed me ſeriouſly to peruſe it. But although I was often in his way on purpoſe to waite upon him to receive his commands about it; yet I never heard more of it from him, although this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe betwixt him and me, was many weekes before <hi>Mr. Primates appeale to the Parliament.</hi> Therfore, I ſay, conſidering all theſe things, I muſt have a care how I truſt a twice reconciled Enemy, eſpecially one that hath made ſo many and ſo glorious tranſcendent promiſes to the Nation of England, and all ſorts of honeſt Men contained in it, as hee hath allready done ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall times over, (as is before truly repeated) <hi>AND MAKES NO CONSCIENCE AT ALL</hi> TO <hi>PERFORME ANY ONE OF THEM.</hi> Yet for peace ſake &amp; for affections ſake to my endeared and poore wiſe, I will the <hi>third time</hi> now goe as low in my propoſitions, as poſſible with any ſafety or imaginable ſecurity I can; upon the granting of which, I will ingage to <hi>ſit ſtill</hi> and write no more againſt him, unleſs he breake the engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment firſt. And therfore in order to a <hi>third reconcilement,</hi> I propoſe in the firſt place, <hi>that ſeeing by Common right, ſeverall ancient and moderne statute Lawes yet in force, the Parliaments and Armies fore-cited Declarations, and the Vnanimous confesſion of all Intereſts and parties</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>whatſoever, a new and ſuccesſive Parliament once a yeare, is the undoubted birthright of the people of England</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>&amp; ſeeing by the</hi> GENERALLS <hi>owne forementioned Declarations, this Parliament, THAT NOW IS, IS NO PARLIAMENT AT ALL, nor upon, „his owne principles, never was ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce he declared and avowed they were traitors to their truſt„ which in the yeare</hi> 1648 <hi>he did,</hi> as has bin truly before recited; and ſeeing by his and his Armies owne confeſſion (as is before truly mentioned) <hi>there is no other Safe, Secure, Honeſt or Iuſt way to provide for the calling of future
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99537:15"/>parliaments in England, but by a„ Popular Agreement ſigned amongſt and by the people;</hi> that therfore he would immediately declare, and give good <hi>Cautionary ſecurity,</hi> that within three, ſoure or 5 Moneths time, <hi>the people of England shall chooſe and have ſitting a new Parliament,</hi> either upon the principles of our <hi>Agreement dated at the Tower of London May</hi> 1, 1649: or upon the <hi>principles of their owne forementioned Agreement,</hi> delivered by them to the Houſe of Commons. &amp; upon theſe conditions I will wave all things concerning my ſelfe, or the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lierie of Harraton, or my Freinds related therunto. And further; to manifeſt to all the world, that my preſent <hi>necesſitated and compelled ſtruggleing,</hi> is not to appropriate to my ſelfe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Government, Rule, Domination, Riches or Greatnes;</hi> I will be willing to give my full conſent unto it under my hand and ſeale, that an act shall be paſſed, by this preſent Parliament, <hi>to make me by name uncapable of being choſen of the next Parliament,</hi> or bearing any Office in the Common-wealth of England, dureing its ſitting, or comeing into England, till it bee ſate.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, it may be the <hi>Generall</hi> may be full of Indignation and ſcorne, that ſuch a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as my ſelfe should dare to make ſuch a propoſition to him, of whom it may truly by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his greatnes be ſaid, as it is ſaid in the 41 of Job of the LEVIATHAN, <q>that when he raiſeth up himſelfe, the mighty are afraid, the ſword of him that layeth at him cannot hold: the ſpeare, the dart, nor the habergeon. He eſteemeth iron as ſtraw &amp; braſs as rotten wood. the arrow cannot make him flee: ſling ſtones are turned with him into ſtubble, darts are counted as ſtubble, <hi>he laugheth at the shakeing of a ſpeare;</hi> upon earth there is not his like, <hi>who is made without feare.</hi>
               </q> But if the <hi>Generall</hi> doe rage and ſcorne at what I ſay; In calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes I anſwer him.</p>
            <p>In the firſt-place with the words of himſelfe and his Armie, as they are written in the 70 and laſt page of their <hi>grand Remonſtrance</hi> from St. Albans 16 Novemb: 1648 which thus ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes. <hi>Wee hope</hi> (ſay they) <q>that in Age of ſo much light, mere will or reſolution will not be held forth or purſued againſt what has bin ſaid. But that, what reaſon or righteouſnes, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is in the things which we have ſaid will be conſidered &amp; folowed, nor let it find prejudice with you</q> (meaneing the Parliament) <hi>from any diſdaigne towards thoſe from whom it</hi> comes [being in the condition of an Armie looked upon as ſervants under you] <q>ſince ſervants may ſpeake to their Maſters and ought to be heard &amp; regarded even when they ſpeake for their owne right only, &amp; rather when they ſpeake for the good and ſafety of them they ſerve, but much more, when they ſpeake of that wherein they have ſome joint Intereſt with them; and yet more, when</q> (thoſe their immediate Maſters being themſelves alſo ſervants and truſtees for the benefit of others) <hi>they ſpeake for the Intereſt of thoſe for whom they are employed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the <hi>Generall</hi> shall hold forth nothing but mere will and reſolution againſt what I have heere ſaid, then in the</p>
            <p>Second place, Let me tell both you &amp; him, I am confident of it, very ſpeedily in one Kind or another, he will meet with one way or another, as bad a portion as hee or they did, againſt whom that Remonſtrance was made.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, I anſweer him in the words of the Scripture Samuel 2. 22, 26, 27, 28 and Chapter 23, 2, 3. where David ſpeaking of God ſaith, <hi>With the mercyfull thou wilt shew they ſelfe mercyfull &amp; with the upright man thou wilt shew thy ſelfe upright; with the pure thou wilt shew thy ſelfe pure, and „with the froward thou wilt shew thy ſelfe unſavoury„ and the afflicted peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thou wilt ſave, „but thine eyes are upon the haughtie„ that thou maieſt bring them downe.</hi> And David further goeing on ſaith, <hi>the Spirit of the Lord ſpake by me, and his word was in my ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, the God of Iſrael ſaid, the rock of Iſrael ſpake to me: „He that ruleth over men muſt be juſt, ruleing in the feare of God.„</hi> And alſo I further anſwer with thoſe ſayings of the Spirit of God, in the 2d of Iſay the 11, 12, 13, 14, 15 &amp; the 3d of Iſay the 11, 13, 14, 15, where it is ſaid,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99537:15"/>
               <q>
                  <hi>The lofty lookes of man shall be humbled, and the haughtynes of man shall be lowed downe„</hi> and the Lord alone shall be exalted in that day. For the day of the Lord of Hoſts shall be upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>one that is proud and lofty, upon every one that is lifted up</hi> &amp; he shall be brought low, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon all the <hi>Cedars of Lebanon, that are high, and lifted up,</hi> and upon all the oakes of Bashan, and upon all the high mountaines, and upon all the Hills that are lifted up &amp; upon every high-tower and upon every fenced wall. Woe unto the wicked, it shall be ill with him; for the reward of his hands shall be given him, for <hi>the Lord ſtandeth up to plead and ſtandeth to judge the people,</hi> the Lord will enter into judgement with the Ancients of his people <hi>and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereof,</hi> for yee have eaten up the vineyard, the <hi>Spoile of the poore is in your houſes.</hi> What meane you that you beat my people to peices and grind the faces of the poore ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts? &amp; chap: 5, 15, 16 <hi>And the mighty man shall bee humbled, and the eyes of the lofty shall be humbled</hi> but the Lord of Hoſts shall be exalted in judgement, and God that is holy shall be Sanctified in righteouſnes. And chap: 13, 6, 11. Houle yee for the day of the Lord is at hand, it shall come as a deſtruction from the Almighty, and I will ſaith God pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the World for their evill and the wicked for their iniquity and <hi>I will cauſe the arrogance of the proud to ceaſe, &amp; will lay low the haughtynes of the terrible,</hi> and chap: 23: 9. The Lord of Hoſts hath purpoſ'd it, <hi>to ſtaine the pride of all glory, and to bring into contempt all the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the Earth,</hi> and chapter 24, 5, 6, 20, 21. the Earth alſo is defiled under the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof, becauſe they have tranſgreſſed the Lawes, changed the ordinance, broken the everlaſting covenant. therfore hath the carſe devoured the Earth and they that dwell the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein are deſolate. the Earth shall reele to and fro like a drunkard, and shall be removed like a cottage, and the tranſgreſſion thereof shall be heavy upon it, and it shall ſall and not ariſe againe. And it shall come to paſs in that day, that the <hi>Lord shall punnish the Hoſts of the high ones that are on high, and the Kings of the Earth upon the Earth,</hi> and Chap: 26. 4, 5, 6, 7, 10, 11. truſt ye in the Lord for ever, for in the Lord Jehovah is everlaſting ſtrength, <hi>for he brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth downe them that dwell on high, the loftie Citty he layeth it low,</hi> he layeth it low even to the ground, he bringeth it even to the duſt. the foote shall tread it downe, even <hi>the feet of the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and the ſtepps</hi> of the needy. the way of the juſt is uprightnes; thou moſt upright, doſt weigh the paths of the juſt. But let favour be shewed to the wicked yet will he not learne righteouſnes. In the Land of uprightnes will he deale unjuſtly &amp; will not behold the Majeſtie of the Lord. and chap 28, 2, 3. Behold the Lord hath a mightie and ſtrong one, which as a tempeſt of haile and a deſtroying ſtorme, as a flood of mighty waters overflowing, shall caſt downe to the earth with the hand the Crowne of pride. And Chap: 29, 20, 21. For the the terrible one is brought to naught, and the ſcorner is conſumed and all that watch for iniquity are cut of: that make a man an offender for a word, &amp; lay a ſnare for him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth in the gate. that turne aſide the juſt for a thing of naught. And Chap. 40, 23, 29, 30, 31. Where it is ſaid of God, <hi>that the bringeth Princes to nothing and maketh the judges of the earth as vanity,</hi> and giveth power to the faint, and to them that have no might hee increaſeth ſtrength. Even the youths shall faint and be weary, and the young men shall utterly fall, but they that waite upon the Lord shall renew their ſtrength: they shall mount up with wings as Aegles; they shall run, and not be weary; they shall walke, and not faint.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, I anſwer, when God will have athing brought to paſs, the ſounding of Ramms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hornes shall be ſufficient to blow downe the walls of Jericho Joshua the 6. <hi>For when God will worke who shall let him? Iſay</hi> 33.13. And when the Allmighty will have a man to act, in deſperate &amp; viſibly improbable deſignes for him, he will compaſs him about, with ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſityes to goe on with his worke, that there is no evadeing it, and put him into Jeremies condition (as many times I my ſelfe have bin) when he forced him to cry out. <q>O Lord, thou haſt deceived me, &amp; I was deceived, thou art ſtronger then I, thou haſt prevailed: I am
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99537:16"/>in deriſion daily, every one mocketh me.</q> For ſince I ſpake, I cryed out, I cryed, Violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and ſpoile; becauſe the word of the Lord was made a reproach unto me, and deriſion dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. then ſaid I, I will not make mention of him, nor ſpeake any more in his name. BUT HIS WORD WAS WITHIN ME, AS A BURNING FIRE SHUT UP IN MY BONES, AND I <q>WAS WEARY WITH FORBEAREING, AND I COULD NOT STAY. For I heard the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fameing of many, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare on every ſide. Report, ſay they, and wee will report it: all my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliars watched for my halting, ſaying, peradventure he will be intiſed and wee shall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile againſt him, and we shall take our revenge on him. But the Lord is with me, as a MIGHTY TERRIBLE ONE, therfore my perſecutors shall ſtumble and they shall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile: they shall be greatly ashamed, for they shall not proſper, their everlaſting confuſion shall never be forgotten. But O Lord of Hoſts that tryeſt the righteous and ſeeſt the rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and the heart, let me ſee thy vengeance on them for unto thee have I opened my cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, bee not a terrour unto me, thou art my hope in the day of evill. LET THEM BE CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FOUNDED THAT PERSECUTE ME, but let not me be confounded, let them be diſmayed, but let not me be diſmayed; BRING UPON THEM THE DAY OF EVILL, AND DESTROY THEM WITH DOUBLE DESTRUCTION <bibl>Jeremy 20, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. and chap. 17. 17, 18.</bibl>
               </q> And give me leave without offence to ſay to my Lord <hi>Generall Cromwell,</hi> as God in ſomething the like caſe ſaid in the 22 Jeremy 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. Woe unto him that buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <q>his houſe by unrighteouſnes, and his chambers by wrong, that uſeth his neighbours ſervice without wages, and giveth him not for his work: that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith, I will build me a wide houſe and large chambers, and cutteth him out windores, and it is ſeeled with cedar, and painted with vermilion. Shalt thou reigne, becauſe thou clotheſt thy ſelfe in Cedar? <hi>did not thy Father eat and drinke and doe judgment and juſtice and then it was well with him?</hi> he jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the cauſe of the poore and the needie, then it was well with him, was not this to know me, ſaith THE LORD? But thine eyes and thine heart, are not but for thy Coveteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and FOR TO SHED INNOCENT BLOOD, and for oppreſſion and for violence to doe it. therfore, ſaith the Lord, thou shalt be buryed with the buryal of an Aſſe, without lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, ſaying AH MY BROTER! or AH LORD! or AH HIS GLORY!</q> Therfore let not the <hi>Generall</hi> for all his greatnes deſpiſe the day of ſmall things. For who would have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leived or immagined 10 yeares agoe, that <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> a meane private inconſiderable man in compariſon, should by this day have had 3 Nations at his becke and command [for I am ſure of it when he &amp; I about 10 yeares agoe by the Parliaments authoritie were firſt made captains, my particular Intereſt in England, was ſoe far beyond his, that <hi>I could then have eaſily raiſed a hundred volenteers to have followed my banner for his one,</hi>] and injoy really a greater po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in them, then ever any of there moſt <hi>Abſolute Kings</hi> this 500 yeares had.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, I anſwere that I have heard from travellers that the ELEPHANT (which of all the beaſts in the world is the moſt warlike one, carrying a Caſtle able to ſecure many men upon it's backe and being in many places in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> ſoe expert in warr, that if an Iron chaine be tyed to its trunke, it will with it mowe downe whole rows of men, and yet for all this) of all the creatures in the world is the moſt affraid of the little ſilly contemptible <hi>piſmire,</hi> the which if it Creepe up it's trunke and git into it's brains (as ſome tyms they doe) the <hi>little crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> will more mad, that <hi>great, furious, ſtrong beaſt,</hi> then the shakings of multitudes of ſpeares, and the powring of shewers of warlike darts and arrows upon it.</p>
            <p>I wish my LORD GENERALL for his owne ſake haveing done ſoe great things in England as he hath done, may ſeriously conſider what he will git at my hands when he hath done the worſt he can to me, for if I fall I can (as I have often through the goodnes of God) riſe againe, but ſoe can not he, for his fall if it come will bee ſoe great, it will breake his necke; and I looke upon him as my grand adverſary, and againſt great nor ſmall muſt I now not fight,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99537:16"/>nor conteſt with to the purpos, <hi>ſaveing only himſelfe;</hi> And truly I am apt to thinke (how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptable ſoever he may Judge me to be) that if he force me to it to the utmoſt neſeſſitie; I shal be able (through the ſtrength of almighty God) to trouble him as bad, as the greateſt Army of Cavileers that ever he fought with in his life did, and to make his very hartſtrings to ake for <hi>skin for skin yea all that a man hath will he give for his life;</hi> But peace with him, (not only for my owne good, but the good and benifit of the whole Nation) is the thing I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire from my hart and ſoule.</p>
            <p>Therefor, I will heere preſume to advice him as Joab adviſes David, when he had like to have taken in the <hi>City of Rabbath,</hi> and therefore adviſed him, <hi>to gather his people together &amp; take it in himſelfe, leaſt he tooke it, and it should be called by his name.</hi> even ſoe, ſay I, a <hi>New Parliament</hi> is the people of Englands right, and the obtaineing of one for them, is even at the very doore, I am ſure of it; therfore let my <hi>Lord Generall</hi> ariſe, and gather his Army about him, and effectually, and in good earneſt revive his or our <hi>Agreement</hi> and ſpeedily procure thereby a <hi>New Parliament</hi> for the people, which I dare avow, infalliby to demonſtrate, <hi>he may as easily, freely and ſafely doe it, if he will but ſay the word, as kiſs his owne hand,</hi> &amp; I will maintaine it he hath no real <hi>dureable ſafety in the world,</hi> but in the doeing of it. but I thinke <hi>Politicus</hi> in his notable preambles to his <hi>thurſday newes-bookes,</hi> hath already ſufficiently clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that point. I ſay therfore, if he will in the hearts of the honeſt and underſtanding people of England be eſteemed and bee really their darling, let him ariſe and doe it with all his might quickly, leaſt I or ſome other <hi>contemptible</hi> or unthought of inſtrument or inſtruments, doe it for the people in <hi>deſpight of him,</hi> and ſo run away with the honour of it, <hi>and have it called by our name.</hi> For let him remember, when the <hi>Scots</hi> firſt invaded England in the yeare 1639 by their declareing <q>they came in for to procure the English people their liberties <hi>and that they might enjoy a Parliament,</hi> which they had bin without ten or eleven yeares together, they tied the Kings hands behind his back therby, and won the Zealous ſtout English peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hearts away from him, and thereby procured for the English People a Parliament in ſpight of the teeth of all that oppoſed it.</q> Nay and thereby made the Kings owne Soldiers <hi>knock their commanders on the head,</hi> that were leading them againſt the ſaid Scots. I ſay no more at preſent, but bid himſelfe make the farther application, only adding, that I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of it, that hee will be the highlyeſt eſteemed man to the people of England, that is in the world, that can or shall be an Inſtrument upon the principles aforeſaid, to procure a <hi>New Parliament</hi> for them, thereby rationally &amp; probably to free &amp; deliver them from their unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable and un-imaginable oppreſſion, bondage and ſlavery which they are under, <hi>worſe and greater by a thouſand degrees then ever it was in the worst of the late Kings times.</hi> For now, I will maintaine it, there is no man in England, that can rationally or upon any probable grounds call either <hi>his land, his trade, his Estate, his life, his wife</hi> or <hi>his children his owne,</hi> or be ſure to enjoy them free from violence one ſingle day to an end. And in the multitude of inſtances, I need to give you no more then mine owne which is now upon me.</p>
            <p>For, have I done the Generall, or the Nation or any particular man in it any wrong, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion or injuſtice? if it be ſaid I have, <hi>I challenge the sight of my whole charge and a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar declaration, that I shall enjoy the benefit of the Petition of right, and the Parliaments and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls paſs freely to come into England„ and there to ſtay for a time and returne back againe, without let or moleſtation, and I doe hereby engage with ſpeed to meet</hi> (by Gods aſſiſtance) <hi>the greateſt and ſtouteſt adverſary that I have in England there at the barr of iuſtice.</hi> And I am ſure, if they can legally prove me guilty of any wickednes or oppreſſion acted upon but the meaneſt man in England, my reputation is gone, and then all my Intereſt in that nation is not worth a groat. So that afterward the <hi>Generall</hi> need not in the leaſt to be afraid of any thing that I can ſay or doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. For then it would ſignifie no more then the wind that blowes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:99537:17"/>Sir, to draw towards a Concluſion. As the <hi>Generall uſed to give his earthly Lords, Maſiers &amp; Creators the Parliament, a few and ſet number of dayes viz:</hi> 4 <hi>or</hi> 5 <hi>at moſt, to anſwer his demands in: ſo from the date hereof, I give you three weekes, or one and twenty daies exclusive,</hi> to returne me what anſwer you pleaſe about this Letter, promiſſing till they be paſt, not to print and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish it; <hi>provided,</hi> by the very firſt poſt after this, you write me word you have received it, or elſe I shall <hi>judge Mr. Thomas Scot hath catcht it„</hi> as I am informed from London, he hath allready done ſome other of my Letters. for which, <hi>and for ſetting his ſpies upon me in theſe Countries, which I have very visibly found out, and for all his old roguery exerciſed towards me,</hi> and plotted againſt me, I muſt be forced when I am a little at leiſure in print to pay him: and particularly for all his notorious <hi>codpeice Simony</hi> that I know of, in attempting to <hi>lie with two of my female Freinds at one time</hi> and <hi>in one bed in the ſame chamber,</hi> at the <hi>ſugar-loafe neare the Muſe by Charing-croſs,</hi> being one of thoſe many <hi>Lecherous houſes</hi> he haunts and hath the command of. Which COLONEL THOMAS PRIDE now a Member of the Armie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moneths agoe at the <hi>Parliament doore TOLD Mr. SCOT partly of to his face,</hi> but he the ſaid Scot durſt never queſtion him therfore, nor the two woemen that (as I remember the Story from <hi>Colonel Prides mouth</hi>) were then mentioned to him to be the parties; and for his ſtrong attempting <hi>to hire one of my quondam Freinds</hi> with the guift of <hi>two hundred pound land a yeare,</hi> firmely to be ſetled upon him and his heirs for ever, to ſweare againſt me at <hi>Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> at my late tryall to take away my life. I ſay, if it come into his hands, I beleive the <hi>Generall</hi> shall never ſee this Letter, till he ſee it in print, which I deſire to avoid if it be pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
            <p>It may be, at the ſight of this, the <hi>Generall</hi> will be mad, and revenge himſelfe on my <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state,</hi> and my <hi>Wife</hi> and <hi>poore Children.</hi> But let him take heed what he doth, for it is the Judgement of Chriſt, <hi>that the ſame meaſure a man meats should be meaſured to him againe.</hi> And the truth of it is, if my ſentence, to morrow, WERE TAKEN OF, 1500 POVND would not, all things conſidered, <hi>in my worldly buſynes,</hi> ſet me in ſo good a condition as I was in, the day before it paſſed againſt me. For being in many intanglements in the world, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veing ſcarce recovered to ſtand upright upon mine owne leggs, it hath allready as good as broke my back, with reference to the world. And in my abſence, I heare every unworthy man, that can but pretend any thing againſt me, to reach me or my poore wife, takes his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of my abſence to abuſe her, and trample upon her. And SIR ARTHUR HASIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIG, I heare, muſt be doeing againe, <q>with his groſs Knave William Huntington of Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingham in the County of Durham,</q> againſt <hi>both of whoſe baſe and lying dealeings with</hi> me, preferred to the Parliament in November laſt againſt me, I made my particular and cleare defence, to the then ſilenceing of them both, in a sheet and an halfe of paper, and preſented it in print to the Parliament the 28 of November 1651 being incitled, <q>to every individuall Member of the ſupreme Authority the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England <hi>The humble Addreſs of Lieutenant Colonel Iohn Lilburne,</hi> by way of anſwer to a moſt <hi>falſe and ſcandalous printed Petition</hi> delivered at the Houſe doore againſt him, <hi>by one William Huntington</hi> upon Weddenſday the 26 of November 1651.</q> In which I am confident I have made as cleare, rational and juſt a defence for my ſelfe, as any man in the World, can ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to any accuſation laid unto his charge, unto which to this very day I never ſaw any thing by way of reply, neither doe I beleive its posſible rationally and juſtly to reply any thing yet unto it. And I hereby bid defiance to him &amp; all my adverſaryes I have in England, to lay a farthing tokens-worth of baſenes juſtly to my charge for 15 yeares together.</p>
            <p>And I wish with all my ſoule, you would ſeriouſly read <hi>my ſaid defence,</hi> my wife being able to furnish you therwith. But further, if I have wronged the man, which I abſolutely deny in the lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, that I have done it, to the value of a ſingle pin: <hi>I proffered him many times
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99537:17"/>faire enough,</hi> as in the ſaid defence you may read, but he would never accept thereof, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, <hi>the Law was open</hi> for him when I was in England and ſtill is, <hi>and is his inheritance as well as mine,</hi> and though I be heere beyond the ſeas, ſo that he cannot arreſt me; yet let him put in his Declaration in a legal Court in England, <hi>as its commonly there reputed,</hi> and ſend me a Copie thereof &amp; I will give Authority to a Freind to anſwer it legally. <hi>for the Law is yet my inheritance, and the heart of the greateſt and ſtoutest man in England, I will make to ake if poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly I can, that shall endeavour to deprive me of the benefit thereof, allthough</hi> I <hi>die at his feet ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi> But let not Sr. ARTHUR HASILRIG take upon him arbitrarily to arbitrate my eſtate, as I heare he is about to doe, when I give him no power and authority ſo to doe. If he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in it, it will but ad unto <hi>that great guilt of his,</hi> that I am perſwaded in time will juſtly carry him to the <hi>Scaffold at Tower-hill</hi> or elſe where, which I <hi>beleive</hi> I <hi>shall live to ſee with mine owne eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir; if towards peace I receive not a ſatisfactory anſwer to this Epiſtle, I muſt deale truly with you, my condition already is ſuch, that it will force me with all the <hi>Eloquence</hi> &amp; <hi>Retho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric</hi> that I have, to cry out aloud, as the Parliament in the day of their diſtreſe did when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired and deſired, <hi>all thoſe that had any ſenſe of piety, honour or compaſsion, to come forth and helpe a diſtreſſed ſtate, part</hi> 1 <hi>of the Booke of their Declarations page</hi> 498. ſo, muſt and shall I by Gods aſſiſtance, with the <hi>mournfulleſt dittyes</hi> and bleeding teares of oppreſſion cry out for <hi>helpe &amp; ſupply,</hi> that my ſoule is able to powre out, <hi>either to God, to Men, or Woemen, of all Nations, relations and conditions</hi> (and publish it as farras <hi>English, Dutch, French</hi> or <hi>Latine</hi> wil carry them, eſpecially to all <hi>truehearted English-men,</hi> that have <hi>fought</hi> for their <hi>Liberties and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, or ſtood by the ſtuff whiles others did it,</hi> who ought to have as good a share in the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties contended for, <hi>as thoſe ſonns of wickednes and Belial as David calls them</hi> 1 <hi>Sam:</hi> 30.22. that would now ingroſs all to themſelves. Who though Chriſtians in name, may yet infinitely be condemned and reproved <hi>by the Righteouſnes and juſtice</hi> OF NEHEMIAH, though a jew, in the like caſe. <q>Who although he 12 yeares together was Governour over his Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in martial and civil affaires in the daies of their diſtreſs, <hi>yet neither he nor his Brethren all that time did eat the bread of the Government, nor bought any land,</hi> but provided for ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers at his owne coſt, and at his owne table: <hi>becauſe of the reproach of the heathen their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies &amp; becauſe of the feare of God.</hi> 
                  <bibl>Nehem: 5.9, 14, 15, 16.</bibl>
               </q>, Nay he would not ſuffer the rich men in that day to exact uſury of the poore men. and righteous <hi>Abraham</hi> (though not ſo full of religious pretences as the <hi>Lord Generall Cromwel</hi>) when he had <hi>redeemed from Captivity</hi> by force of Armes the People of the <q>wicked Citty Sodome, <hi>whoſe King would have given him for his paines all the goods he had redeemed with them;</hi> yet he ſcorned it, and would not take any thing that was his or theirs, noe not to the value of a show-latchet, <hi>leaſt the heathen should ſay he had made Abraham rich,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Geneſis 14, 15, 22, 23.</bibl>
               </q> I ſay I muſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to all ſorts of people to cry out bitterly for helpe and aſſiſtance, to enable me to print thouſands and ten thouſands of my mournfull ditties and lamentations, and to beare the charges of my meſſengers and agents, by whom I muſt ſend them gratis, into all the parts &amp; coaſts of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland; and all the Iſles thereunto belonging;</hi> that poſſibly I can get them conveighed unto. and I doubt not; but allthough the <hi>Magiſtrates of Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> have allready ſeazed upon ſome of my <hi>Apologies</hi> and thereby ſtopt the public ſale of them, being almoſt <hi>ten-sheets of paper</hi> in ENGEISH AND DUTCH, yet that I shall either beg or borrow mony enough, to inable me within a little time, to give them, and ten thouſands of other <hi>printed papers away gratis.</hi> For I doubt not, but the Spirit of magnanimity, zeale &amp; conſcience will worke ſo powerfully in ſome of my <hi>rich Countreymen</hi> &amp;c. (that now have no aſſurance by reaſon of that arbitrary and tyrannicall power they are under of keepeing what they poſſeſs and enjoy, nor of their lives, nor of their <hi>Liberties, wives nor children,</hi> to find out
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99537:18"/>wayes and meanes to ſend me a ſupply of money, to inable me like a man of mettle, courage and induſtry; to ſtruggle for the obtaineing of a <hi>New Parliament for them and my ſelfe:</hi> to bind up, heale and cure; all the breaches of our greatly diſtreſſed and diſtempered Nation: &amp; thereby to ſecure unto them and my ſelfe the Free enjoyment of our <hi>ancient ond undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted birth-right liberties,</hi> that ſo in peace and quietnes with rejoyceing and <hi>praiſing of God,</hi> for all his Fatherly goodnes and loveing kindnes manifeſted to <hi>poore England,</hi> we may ſit dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in <hi>ſecurity, peace,</hi> &amp; <hi>tranquillity</hi> of mind, under our <hi>owne vines.</hi> So committing you, as my owne ſoule, to the ſweet and gracious protection of the Lord God allmighty, <hi>the rock &amp; Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uge,</hi> of all thoſe that truly have a portion in him, I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Study at Mrs. BEZARS HOUSE <hi>in Sheepes-alley</hi> in the Holy-way-ſtreet, IN AMSTERDAM <date>this preſent <hi>Fry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> being the 2 April 1652. old Style.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours and Englands true and through-pac 't Friend JO: LIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BURNE, SEMPER IDEM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Doe aſſure you I tooke all the care that posſibly I could, that this foregoeing Letter, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to your faſt and real Freind <hi>Mr. William Kiffen</hi> might be delivered to your Lordship, but ſeeing I have ſtaid the outrunning of the time I did prefix in the 30 page foregoeing, and have not heard one word as yet from any body in the world, what is become of it. Although I writ divers Letters to ſeverall perſons, ſignifieing that I had ſent ſuch an Epiſtle over, yea &amp; alſo gave a hint of it to your Lordship in my Letter to your ſelfe ſent by the Poſt, the Copie of which thus foloweth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>For his Excellency the LORD GENERALL CROMWELL theſe perſent.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>AT my diſcourſe with you in your Gallery about 4 or 5 Moneths agoe, I had thought I had given your Lordship ſo full ſatisfaction in every thing, that might <hi>remove all jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> from you, of my <hi>diſſerveing</hi> you in any Kind; that of all men in the Parliament, I little imagined to have found your honour to be the principall man <hi>to bannish me</hi> into a ſtrange Countrie, where for the Safety of my Life I am forced to print <hi>an Apologie.</hi> And becauſe you are named in it, I judge it but manlike to ſend you a Copie of it. And, if I had not bin travailing laſt poſt day, I had ſent it to you then. And I have alſo by this poſt ſent to a Freind three sheeres of Paper in writing to communicate to your Lordship. the which, if you pleaſe to read them, you will find that you are deeply concerned in them.</p>
                  <p>I have no more to ſay to your honour, but to deſire God for you <hi>(if it be his pleaſure)</hi> to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke you ſpeedily as righteous in actions, as you were ſome yeares agoe in Declarations, and to take leave to ſay, I am yet as much honeſt</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Amſterdam</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>April</hi> 2 1652</date> 
                        <hi>Old ſtyle.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>JOHN LILBURNE as ever I was in my life, that neither <hi>loves Flattery,</hi> nor feares <hi>Greatnes or Threatning.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>ANd now my Lord, beſides that <hi>Apologie</hi> which I ſent your Honour, I have alſo here in <hi>Dutch and English</hi> printed the <hi>reaſons</hi> wherefore I was neceſſitated to print <hi>that Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99537:18"/>and they are dated they 4 <hi>of March laſt</hi> old ſtyle. and in the ſaid <hi>Apologie</hi> to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> pag: 71 I promiſed them ſpeedily to print <hi>in Dutch</hi> the <hi>manifeſtation</hi> &amp; <hi>Agreement of the</hi> 1 <hi>of May</hi> 1649 <hi>therein named.</hi> which, being <hi>two sheets,</hi> I have accordingly prepared for them, with about as much more additions by way of <hi>appendix</hi> to my <hi>Apologie.</hi> But ſeeing that upon the Magiſtrates ſtopping the public ſelling my ſaid <hi>Apologie</hi> and by the „cheife Scout or high-Sherif of Amſterdam„ giveing me ſome reaſons therefore, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got from me this Replication: <q>that I was a man commonly reputed to have ſome ſtock of reaſon in me, but being but a private individual man, and alſo a ſtranger of another Nation and banished from thence, and come here to take up ſanctuary, and therfore in mine owne underſtanding I should judge my ſelfe totally void of reaſon or judgement, if I should preſs to enjoy that at their hands, which they themſelves judged pręjudicial to their whole nation, or any part of it, they themſelves alone (and not I in the leaſt), being the only and proper Judges of their owne good and well fare; and therfore with all reſpect to them muſt acquieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in their pleaſure.</q> In this regard I ſay <hi>(my Lord]</hi> to avoid offence, I judge it not fit to <hi>publish</hi> the ſaid <hi>Appendix</hi> till ſuch time as one where or an other, I can freely <hi>obtaine licence,</hi> to print <hi>avowedly,</hi> what in that kind I have to ſay.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>(my Lord)</hi> it may be, ſeverall of my Freinds in England, may wonder why all this ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, I have not published the full ſtate of the caſe betwixt <hi>Sr. Arthur Haſilrig, Mr. Primate and my ſelfe.</hi> But, I muſt <hi>Apologize</hi> for my ſelfe, that to ſecure my perſon and reputation hath taken me up much time, as alſo the Magiſtrates ſtopping my <hi>Apologetical Narration,</hi> hath forced me to ſpend much money and time to travell and looke out for my ſelfe, where Safely to abide and print without offence Beſides, that buſynes is a long worke, &amp; although I brought over with me <hi>above</hi> 150 <hi>sheetes of written paper</hi> of that buſynes, as it was taken at the ſaid committee <hi>in short-hand;</hi> yet for a long time, I have wanted ſome part of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and latter end of it, as alſo copies of ſeverall orders and of depoſitions, &amp; I could not for want thereof goe on with it, but now by Gods aſſiſtance I shall apply my ſelfe unto it, with all the vigour that poſſibly I can.</p>
            <p>And this, before I conclude, give me leave further to aver unto your Lordship. <hi>I am an English-man borne and bred,</hi> &amp; to breath in the ayre of England, is as much my right as yours; &amp; I have conteſted &amp; fought with my ſword in my hand for the enjoyment of my share in the Lawes &amp; Liberties thereof, &amp; never was convicted of doeing any action that forſeited my por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therein. And therfore, by the aſſiſtance of God, I will turne all the ſtones in the world, that it is poſſible for a reſolute man &amp; an induſtrious man &amp; a man of braines to turne, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke way for my comeing to England againe &amp; for my liveing there, <hi>in a rational ſecurity,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in the indeavouring thereof, I run the hazard of being expoſed to all the miſeryes and deaths, that it is poſſible for a man to be expoſed to. And yet I hope, through the ſtrength of God, I shall undertake nothing, <hi>but righteous and honeſt wayes for the procureing thereof.</hi> But this I aſſure you my Lord, I groundedly thinke, that I or any man elſe that will not be your <hi>abſolute ſlave,</hi> can never live in a <hi>rational &amp; probable Safety</hi> in England, ſo long as your will is an <hi>abſolute Law</hi> there. Therefore, <hi>My Lord,</hi> ſit as <hi>faſt</hi> as you can: In the ſtrength of the Lord God almighty, have at you; <hi>and if I perish I perish.</hi> But if you will let us have in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>new and annuall Parliaments,</hi> upon the termes before premiſed, I have done, &amp; in your doeing thereof shall reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to ſerve you therein, JOHN LILBVRNE.</signed>
               <dateline>From my lodgeing at that <hi>pleaſant City</hi> of much refuge, that <hi>little Zoar,</hi> commonly called VIANEN <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 1652.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>POSTSCRIPT, <hi>My Lord,</hi> if you ſet any of your Champions to write againſt me, be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re they ſet their Names to their diſcourſes, or elſe truly <hi>my Lord</hi> I shall take you your ſelfe for the Author of every paper that comes out againſt me, &amp; ſo nominally reply upon you.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
